<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and faithful narrative of the unjust and illegal sufferings, and oppressions of many Christians ... in the county of Devon, since the tenth of May, 1670 ... as also, of the most malicious prosecution of nine innocent persons ... : and of the tryals that were betwixt Matthew Hele ... William Bastard ... and Mr. Edmund Reynel, and John Bear ... at the Assizes held at Exon, in the county of Devon, April 1671.</title>
            <author>Hickes, John, 1633-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12086949</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12086949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 73:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and faithful narrative of the unjust and illegal sufferings, and oppressions of many Christians ... in the county of Devon, since the tenth of May, 1670 ... as also, of the most malicious prosecution of nine innocent persons ... : and of the tryals that were betwixt Matthew Hele ... William Bastard ... and Mr. Edmund Reynel, and John Bear ... at the Assizes held at Exon, in the county of Devon, April 1671.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, John, 1633-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to J. Hickes. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution --  England --  Devon.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53767:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53767:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE AND FAITHFUL Narrative, Of the Unjuſt and Illegal Sufferings, and Oppreſsions of many Chriſtians (Injuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Injudiciouſly call'd <hi>FANATICKS,</hi> holding all the Fundamentals of the Chriſtian Religion, Believing all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith; and whoſe Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations are as Conſonant, and Agreeable to the Laws of God as theirs that Perſecute them) under, and by ſeveral of his Majeſties Juſtices of Peace, and others, who are no Officers, but Informers, in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> ſince the Tenth of <hi>May,</hi> 1670 from a pretended Zeal, to put the Law againſt <hi>Conventicles</hi> in Execution.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, Of the moſt Malicious Proſecution of Nine Innocent Perſons, to take away their Lives, under a Falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Murdering an Informer: And of the Tryals that were betwixt <hi>Matthew Hele,</hi> of <hi>Halwel,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Pool, William Baſtard,</hi> of <hi>Garſton,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Weſt-Alvington,</hi> Eſquires, and Mr. <hi>Edmund Reynel,</hi> and <hi>John Bear,</hi> (Called by a Nick-name <hi>Cocky Bear</hi>) Two Informers for pretended Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, of putting the Act againſt <hi>Conventicles</hi> in Execution, and the hard Meaſure they met with from the Judg; with the Horrid Perjuries of the Witneſſes brought againſt them, at the <hi>Aſſizes</hi> held at <hi>Exon,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon, April</hi> 1671.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53767:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53767:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not neceſſary, that thou ſhould know who hath Compos'd, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed, the enſuing Narrative, I ſhall only thus Characterize him to thee, that he is an Enemy to none that is a Friend to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his glorious Goſpel; that he doth not value men by their moſt ſplendid Profeſſion, but ſerious practice of Religion; not by Religious Notions, but by a Religious Nature; nor by being of a Party, but by the practice of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; not by a not intemperate Zeal, either for Negative, or poſſitive Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the ſlender Circumſtances, but the Vital parts, and ſubſtance of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. He loves, eſteems, and prefers an Epiſcopal perſon, that's a ſtrict, and cloſe walker with God, whoſe Life is conſonant, and whoſe Actions are correſpondent to that compleat and perfect Rule, which Divine Laws do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute; before a prophane <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> or <hi>Independant,</hi> &amp;c. and a Pious, Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conformiſt, before a looſe and laſie Non-conformiſt, when he knows it is ſo, though he muſt confeſs according to his Obſervation; the latter are not generally ſo morally Criminous, and Peccant as the former. He heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, that in theſe three Nations, all were of a pacate Spirit, and peaceable Deportment towards each other, and that every one were diſpoſſeſt of a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious Devil. And as he doth not think any form of Civil Regiment, to be of Divine Right, ſo he can Honour, and Pray for the Governments that God doth ſet over us; and though he earneſtly deſires that all may anſwer the end of Goverment, which is the Advancement of the Common Good (this being the will of the Univerſal Rector, as his Supream Law, or Rule in Politicals) and that every Law of theirs may be Congruous, and not contrary to the Laws of the <hi>Supream Monarch,</hi> and higheſt Legiſlator; and that all may have their Foundation in <hi>Right Reaſon,</hi> and common <hi>Equity,</hi> which may make their Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation unqueſtionable, and give the <hi>Eſſe</hi> of a Law indeed to them; yet when they are not ſo, though he cannot yield an <hi>Active Obedience</hi> to them, yet he can a <hi>Paſſive</hi> Subjection to the Magiſtrate that makes them; diſtinguiſhing between the Authority of his Laws, and of his Perſon, ſo that though he judgeth not the former Obliging to his Conſcience (or to ſpeak as properly that his Conſcience binds not to ſuch Laws) yet he doth the Latter to his outward man, to keep it from reſiſting when Puniſhed, though he could avoid ſuch Puniſhment by Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>He wiſheth that the Smiles, and Favours of <hi>Royal Majeſty,</hi> may be as a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>Balſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me,</hi> to heal thoſe many Wounds that are now made in our Body Politick, that it may at laſt be reduced to an <hi>Eucraſy,</hi> or a <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Conſtitution;</hi> but if that cannot or muſt not be, he equally deſireth, that they who feel the Smart, that Sigh, and Groan under the Anguiſh of them, may be of a Sedate Spirit, and to be perſwaded unto a patient Tolleration thereof; till the chiefeſt Phyſitian by his Infallible and unerring Wiſdom,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53767:3"/> contrive and provide a remedy that may inſallably, and with irreſiſtable <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nergy,</hi> effecteth the Cure.</p>
            <p>He will not charge it upon any of our <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> that they have made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and Unjuſtifiable Laws, to be as Swords, and Spears to make theſe deep and dangerous Wounds; to <hi>Vulnerate</hi> almoſt <hi>Mortally</hi> the greateſt part of the Political Body, to gratifie a few Members thereof; but he aſſerts that an Illegal execution of Laws, makes theſe freſh-bleeding Wounds, which the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Narrative will preſent to thy Vew, and which I hope, if thou beeſt but either a truly Pious, or <hi>Right Noble,</hi> and <hi>Generous</hi> Soul, thou cannot look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without pitty, and a compaſſionate <hi>Reſentment.</hi> Not only Piety but Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity is productive of higheſt Compaſſions, and Commiſſerations. I hold it more Eligible by far to fall into the hands of a man, that hath a Soul bravely <hi>Impregnated</hi> with that principle (ſuppoſing him to want the other) then of him; whoſe Soul was ſcarce ever Elevated, and raiſed a Degree above a Dunghil, who Lives and Acts as if it were but the very Origin, and Off-ſpring thereof, knowing, and affecting nothing but Sordidneſs, and Baſeneſs, ſuch a one is moſt Inſolent, Inſulting, and Domineering, Proud, and Scornful, when he hath power, moſt Incommiſerate, and Incompaſſionate, when others ſtand to his Mercy, and he ſees he can Tread, and Trample upon them, he is moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful when he hath an oppertunity, which he is ever greedily waiting for; and what ever is Indecotous for a man to do, or unbecoming Humanity, that will he do; or hath ſtill an innate habit, or principal connatural with him, to act him thereunto, which will break forth, and ſhew it ſelf if not curb'd, or reſtrain'd by ſome forraign force, or external power; for this reaſon, it's alwayes better to have a truly Valiant Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or an Enemy, than a Coward, becauſe if he Conquer, he will very tender of ſpilling Blood, unleſs there be an abſolute Neceſſity that compels him to it. If therefore this Narrative can but have the Honour, and Happineſs to kiſs the Hand, and be Viewed with the Eyes of any truly <hi>Generous</hi> Spirit (which hath ſuch a Law of Nobleneſs Enthron'd in it, as I am ſure it cannot Violate) what ever perſwaſion he be of, I know he cannot but highly diſdain the Actings of ſome, and pitty the the Wrongs, and Oppreſſions of others.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould not Sufferers hope? Our King is of that Manſuete, Milde, and Compaſſionate Temper, that if he did but Read, and had but a right In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of ſuch things as are contained in this Narrative: (But alas! There are too many which endeavour a prevention of their acceſs unto, and arrival at his Eare, and Eyes, or repreſent them in a falſe Glaſs; and this is many times the <hi>Miſery</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> and a conſiderable cauſe of their Miſcariages in Government, that they cannot hear with their own Ears, from thoſe that would give a right Information and true ſtate of Perſons, and things; nor ſee with their own Eyes what is needful to be Expoſed to the View, and lye open to the Obſervation thereof) but he would endeavour ſome ſpeedy Relief for the Oppreſſed, if not grow Big with <hi>Royal Indignation</hi> againſt the Oppreſſers.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not much concern my ſelf, whether this Narrative be Grateful, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>teful to the Reader, ſeeing it's compoſed of Truth; for what I have Collected, and Publiſhed, I have done it with awful Apprehenſions of the ſevere inſpection of God's All-ſeeing Eye; and therefore would not wilfully,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53767:3"/> and wittingly ſend abroad Falſhood to Travel in the World, neither would I deviate or vary from Verity in the moſt minute, and Inconſiderable Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: But if I ſhould, as poſſibly I may, yet I hope I ſhall be pardoned by the Candid Reader, and that he will become an Advocate for me (ſeeing the beſt, and trueſt Hiſtorians are Obnoxious to ſuch miſtakes) ſo long as the Subſtance is true: Which take as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 29th. 1670, Mr. <hi>George Reynel</hi> of <hi>Malſon,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Sherford, Devon</hi> (now a Priſoner in the <hi>Kingsbench</hi>) one of his Majeſties Juſtices of Peace (though a ſufficient diſturber thereof, of which you have ſome ſignal Inſtances in the following Narrative) being informed by ſome <hi>Infamous</hi> fellows (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for that end) that there was an Aſſembly of People at Mr. <hi>John Hicks</hi> his Houſe, (a Non-conformiſt Miniſter) in the Town of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> came thether about Eleven a Clock in the Forenoon, attended with divers Perſons (moſt of which are well known to be Lewd, and Debaucht) and moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly attempts to Break open the Street-door, with an Iron Bar, or Sledg of Iron, which not being able ſpeedily to do, his Brother, <hi>Arthur Reynel,</hi> goes to the Back-door, which being open, he enters, and haſtens to the other, and not finding the Key in the Lock, begins to Curſe (judgd by ſome a minute Crime in compariſon of Praying, and Preaching the Goſpel) in this manner, the <hi>Plague</hi> take you, throw too it; but the Key being ſpeedily found, the Door was opened to the Juſtice, and his Attendants; who without delay, having entred the Houſe, preſently aſcends to the Chambers (leaving his Brother <hi>Arthur</hi> and ſome others below) and enquires for the ſaid Mr. <hi>H.</hi> being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but not proved, to have Preacht; whom not finding, moſt unbecoming a Gentleman, and a Juſtice of Peace, before his Wife, Reviles, and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niates, calling him then, and at the Tavern after, <hi>Rebel, Rogue, Raſcal, Town-Bull, Whore-Maſter, Baſtard-Maker,</hi> &amp;c. Then he above, and his Brother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, begin to take the Names of the People whom they found there; but in vain was the Aſſay, for both their Hands Trembled ſo much (which was Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the View and Obſervation of many Spectators, who are ready now to Atteſt it) that they could not ſcarce write one Name, and ſo were for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t to deſiſt. What was Productive, or Cauſative of this <hi>Paralytical Diſtemper,</hi> I leave the Intelligent, and Impartial Reader to Judg. Yet notwithſtanding, the ſaid Juſtice (<hi>as</hi> if he <hi>would</hi> attempt a Conqueſt over the Terrors of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and would Baffle, and Stifle the Conſternating Convictions of his own <hi>Conſcience</hi>) proceeds <hi>May</hi> the 30th. to a Coviction of ſeveral Perſons to ſuffer, as he pretended, according to the Law made againſt Conventicles. Firſt then, though no Miniſter was found, nor could it be prov'd that there was any, muchleſs that Mr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> or any other Miniſter did either Preach, or Teach (which is the Crime that Incurs the penalty of Twenty Pound) yet be Levied Twenty Pound upon the ſaid Mr. <hi>H.</hi> for Preaching, and iſſues forth his Warrant to the Conſtables of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> to take Deſtreſs upon his Goods (be judging and declaring him upon the ſight of his Houſhold Goods the Sabbath-day, ſufficent to ſatisfie the Law) but he refuſing to open his Doors, the lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eaten againſt Law, transfers the Penalty from him, to ſome of his ſuppoſed Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; and amongſt the reſt, he Levieth Forty Shillings upon one <hi>Roger-B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rd,</hi> who was not the Lords-day before at Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe when the Juſtice came, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53767:4"/> though he made his complaint to him of the wrong done him, yet he would not relieve him: Twenty Shillings he Levied upon <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> who refuſing to pay it, he (<hi>as</hi> if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been too merciful, and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate before) adds Fifteen Shillings more to it, and commands the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to Deſtrain thirty Sheep for it; which is a moſt horrid Oppreſſion, and higheſt Injuſtice, contrary to all Law: As the 51. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. which ſaith, <hi>That Diſtreſſes muſt be reaſonable, after the value of the Debt, and Demand.</hi>— 52. Hen. 3. Which ſaith, <hi>That Deſtreſſes ſhall be reaſonable, and not too great, and he that taketh great, and unreaſonable Deſtreſſes, ſhall be grievouſly Amerced, for the Exceſs thereof.</hi> So 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. 12. Forty Shillings further he Levieth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chriſpin Collings,</hi> who finding himſelf Agrieved, makes his Appeal accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law: And now the Injuſtice, and Oppreſſions that he met with at the <hi>Seſſions,</hi> may be Read. Firſt, when he came up with Witneſſes to prove ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things of Moment, and had been at great Charges, he was not ſuffered to Travers his Appeal, but (as if on purpoſe to Oppreſs him the more, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there could be no Witneſſes then got to prove he was at Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his houſe) made to enter into new Recognizance to do it, the next Seſſions after; which when he came to do, he found <hi>Juſtice ſtood afar</hi> off, and Equity <hi>could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> for there Judgment principally paſt upon the Evidence of an Ignorant <hi>Fellow,</hi> who Swore he ſaw him in the ſaid Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe, and when it was demanded at what time, he reply'd, in the Afternoon, and yet the pretended Conventicle that Mr. <hi>Reynel</hi> would Convict of, was in the Forenoon; and though it could not be prov'd that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> did at that time either Preach or Teach, yet was the ſaid <hi>C. Collings</hi> adjudg'd to part of the Twenty Pound, beſides the Treble Coſt, which was ſcrewed up to the highth. The moſt that could be Atteſted, was that the Voice of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> was heard; and yet he that did Swear this, was at that diſtance from his Houſe, that it rendred it very difficult either to hear the Voice of a Man, or ſo as to diſtinguiſh betwixt the Voice of one man, and another; and impoſſible to know whether it were the Voice of one Praying or Preaching, by the moſt open and attentive Ears; yet this was Valid and Authentick enough, to prove that there was Preaching. But as I have heard of a man that was uſually of the petty <hi>Jury,</hi> for Life, and Death, in the County where he lived, and when Evidence was not clear to the Jury of a Felonious fact, would ſtill ſay, let us hang the man at a Venture: So were moſt of the Juſtices at the Seſſions, and the Jury (which is uſually accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their hearts deſire) reſolv'd to do with <hi>Chriſpin Collings</hi> to make him pay part of the Fine, whether there was Preaching, yea, or no. And this hath been their practice from Seſſions to Seſſions, as ſhall by ſeveral following Inſtances be prov'd.</p>
            <p>Before the next Sabbath, Mr. <hi>Reynel</hi> left the Country, but his <hi>Setters,</hi> or <hi>Informers</hi> continue in it (whether they were Volunteers, and Spontaneous Actors, or ſtired up by him to this <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> work, and <hi>Honourable</hi> imployment, I ſhall not determine) who the enſuing Lords-day were very Active, Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and Induſtrious to diſcharge the truſt repoſed in them after ſometime therefore ſpent in Hunting, they, <hi>Scent</hi> a <hi>Conventicle</hi> near <hi>Surley Butts,</hi> in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Well<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vington,</hi> to which with great Celerity, and Speed, they haſten, and <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>-like, drive moſt furiouſly, leaſt they ſhould miſs of their Game, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53767:4"/> Prey: The conſiderable Circumſtances of which Actions, are as followeth. Firſt, the number of Perſons engaged therein, which were about Fourteen Horſe and Foot. Secondly, their Quality, one or two of them Gentlemen (<hi>in</hi> that <hi>Common, Abſurd,</hi> irrational Notion, and Acceptation of a Gentleman among us, that is one deſcended from ſuch an Ancient, dignified Family, when there is a Degeneration from all the true Noble Accompliſhments, and behaviour of Gentlemen; and a total, and ſhameful Laps from all real Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that true Gentility is the Genuine Off-ſpring of, which it gives its firſt riſe, and being too, and which neceſſarily it muſt have its foundation laid in; when he hath ſcarce a Rag, or Shadow of it left, nothing but Romantick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, Pedantick Poſtures, and Legs made with ſome Geometrical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion) with one Mr. <hi>John Bear,</hi> who is now in a probability to be lickt into ſome form, and ſhape of Gentility, with <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Nicholas F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> what they take themſelves to be, I know not; but I think their Gentility will ſcarce paſs for Currant Coyn in the Country where they live: The reſt were the very Scum thereof, a meer <hi>Catalines</hi> Crew, whoſe Imployment did exactly Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monize, and Correſpond with their Quality; for Durty <hi>Fellows</hi> or moſt fit for Durty work. Thirdly, Their Condition, which is Neceſſitous (for the greateſt part of them) a ſufficient Provocative, and ſpur to theſe Heroick Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Fourthly, The Head of this Informing Party the aboveſaid Mr. <hi>John Beer,</hi> or <hi>Bear</hi> (as he writes after his <hi>Grand-father,,</hi> the <hi>Old Committee-man,</hi> who Uſurpt, and Aſſum'd the Name of <hi>Bear,</hi> which is the Name of another worſhipful Family in <hi>Devon,</hi> to dignifie his own with) of <hi>Woodmaſon,</hi> or <hi>Bears-comb</hi> (as the old <hi>Committee-man</hi> denominated it from his <hi>New Name, Bear</hi>) near <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> this New-ſtampt Gentleman, was the Captain of, and had the honour to Conduct this Peerleſs Party, and Squadron: Of whoſe <hi>Unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Ingenerous,</hi> and <hi>Diſobliging</hi> deportment among his Neighbours, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his <hi>ſordid Actions,</hi> you ſhall have a further and fuller Account. Fifthly, The manner of their coming which was with <hi>urſine</hi> Rage, <hi>Bellaine</hi> Fury, <hi>Impetuous</hi> Inſolency, Beating a Youth in the way, whom they ſuppoſed gave warning to the People; to whom in a moſt outragious manner, at firſt they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, their Renowned and Gallant Leader, Mr. <hi>John Beer,</hi> or <hi>War</hi> (but let us not deny, or grudg him the latter name, it being ſo Congruous to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) his firſt Salution being: Where is that <hi>Damn'd Rogue,</hi> (meaning the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Miniſter) others of them cried out, <hi>Ride</hi> for your <hi>Lives;</hi> which they did without any reſpect to the People in the way: And ſuch were their rude <hi>Voceferations,</hi> and <hi>Exclamations,</hi> with their moſt ſoul Calumniations, that well might any have judg'd ſome <hi>Bedlam</hi>-madneſs to have poſſeſt them, or that they were ſome <hi>Tartarian Troop,</hi> brought by an Inviſible hand thether. And when they could not find the ſaid Miniſter, Mr. <hi>John Bear,</hi> Retreats; and Advancing towards ſeveral Gentle-women (whoſe Virtue and Modeſty, is well known, and acknowledg'd in the Country where they live, by all, but thoſe that have reſpect for, or value neither) begun Prodigiouſly to Curſe them, after this manner: <hi>The Plague take you, What have you done with</hi> Hicks? And then adds to it, <hi>Swearing</hi> by the moſt Sacred, and Terrible Name of the Supream <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: You have hid him under your</hi>— The reſt of his words being ſo Obſcaen and Filthy, I ſhall break off with an <hi>Apoſioperis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53767:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>George Bear,</hi> the younger Brother, coming to a young man, demands of him Ten Shillings; who mildly Replied, Do you want Money? Whereupon the ſaid <hi>G. B.</hi> ſpurs up his Horſe with much Fury and Fierceneſs againſt him, but (as if he were ſenſible of the Inhumanity of his Maſter) he denies Obedience, and Recoyls; then <hi>G. B.</hi> commands one <hi>Lucas</hi> his Informing Brother (a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of vaſt Dimenſions) to Beat him, with theſe words; <hi>Beat the Rogue;</hi> who prenſently with a great Cudgel, moſt furiouſly and forcibly, gave him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Blows upon his Head, bruiſing it very much, and in all probability had he not kept on his Hat, his Life had been endangered: Yet the other took his abuſe very patiently, making not the leaſt reſiſtance. <hi>Tho. Ford,</hi> a moſt buſie and active Informer (having his Soul impregnated with ſuch principles of matchleſs Magnanimity, that one might ſuppoſe there was now a clear demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the <hi>Metempſenchoſis</hi> of Souls, that ſome Hectors, or Scanderbegs, had tranſmigrated into his Body) with moſt <hi>Heroick,</hi> and <hi>Invincible</hi> courage, chargeth three young <hi>Women,</hi> commanding them with moſt <hi>fierce Looks,</hi> and the <hi>Rays</hi> of higheſt <hi>Valour,</hi> ſparkling through his <hi>ſprightly Eyes,</hi> to ſtand for their <hi>Lives,</hi> Minacing, and Threatning moſt formidably, that he would run them thorow, if they would not tell where <hi>Hicks</hi> was; the words were ſo like <hi>Thondering</hi> and <hi>Lightning,</hi> that they were ſtruck into <hi>Conſternation,</hi> and ſome of them through fear <hi>Fainted,</hi> and fell down: If <hi>Ne Hercules contra duos,</hi> What a rare Son of <hi>Mars</hi> was here, that durſt Encounter with three at once. Certainly on Army of ſuch men would have been ſignally Serviceable to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> when the <hi>Dutch</hi> came firſt up to <hi>Chatham,</hi> when all the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> gave a clear Demonſtration by their <hi>Pannick fear,</hi> how little of <hi>Mars</hi> was in them; no doubt if he had been then Imploy'd, he would have merited Immortal honour. And to conclude this, when theſe Informers were together, nothing could ſcarce be heard but whole <hi>Volleys</hi> of <hi>Oaths,</hi> with a moſt execrable Eructation, and Evomition of Curſes, inſomuch that one would have thought <hi>Infernal Spirits</hi> had made uſe of <hi>Corportal Organs.</hi> Some of them were (as the two Informing <hi>Beers</hi>) upon Conviction by Mr. <hi>Baſtard,</hi> of <hi>Garſton,</hi> puniſht according to Law, for Swearing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 12th. theſe <hi>Informers,</hi> with freſh <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> and an Addition to their Number, in a very Hoſtile manner, came into the Town of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> and when they were near Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> his Houſe, they drew their Swords, to the Terrour of ſome of the Inhabitants that were within view thereof, and then haſten to his Houſe to beſet it; the better to effect which, they violently, and furiouſly, broke open his next Neighbours Street-door, and then ſome of them run thorow his Entry, and Garden, and Leaping over the Hedg, came to Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Back-door, that they might forcibly keep in the People (which they ſuppoſed were there) till a <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> came, and Apprehend the ſaid Mr. <hi>H.;</hi> which a few days before, one of the Informers (and that <hi>George Bear,</hi> if I miſtake not) ſaid Fifteen of them had engag'd to the Biſhop of <hi>Exam,</hi> to do. Now let the Reader know that theſe Informers came (as they did the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before) thus Arm'd with Swords, and Piſtols, without any Warrant or Authority from any Juſtice of Peace, and without any Officer with them; the People therefore knowing there was no Authority to Reſtrain, and Deprive them of their Liberty, reſolved to go out at the Back-door, were they found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53767:5"/> one <hi>John Lucas,</hi> a <hi>Carpenter,</hi> with a Piſtol in his hand Cockt, and preſented to them (which <hi>Lucas</hi> was bound to the <hi>Peace,</hi> or <hi>Good Behaviour,</hi> for Beating the man the Lords-day before, of which an Account is given) yet thus they Arm him; when the Piſtol was firſt given him, he quickly and ſpeedily, run to the Back-door of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe, and then returning haſtily again, cry'd our to his Informing Brothren, <hi>Yonder are the Rogues:</hi> But then ſaid, <hi>What ſhall I do with this Piſtol, there is nothing in it?</hi> Upon which words, one of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers was ſeen to deliver him ſomething, which he put into the Piſtol, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted towards the Back-door again, ſaying; <hi>Now I am fitted for the Rogues:</hi> And when he ſtood at the Door, he was further heard to threaten, that he would Piſtol thoſe that came forth; which cauſed two of the Company (viz. <hi>Nicholas Huxome,</hi> and <hi>John Leech</hi>) to diſarm him, to prevent his doing Miſchief (for he that had beaten one the Sabbath before, might kill another now) which when they had done, ſeveral of the Informers came, as Mr. <hi>John Bear,</hi> his Brother <hi>George,</hi> the <hi>Valiant Tom Ford,</hi> &amp;c. to juſtifie him in breaking of the Peace, and with drawn Swords, and cockt Piſtols, they purſue ſome Perſons, threatning to kill them: One of them ſet his point of his naked Rapier to the Breaſt of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (who ſaith, ſhe thinks it was <hi>George Bear</hi>) uttering Bloodily, and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly theſe words: <hi>Thou impudent Jade, or damn'd Whore, I could find in my heart to Run thee thorow, and if I ſhould do it, I ſhould do God good ſervice.</hi> The ſaid <hi>George Bear,</hi> ſet the point of his Rapier to the Breaſt of <hi>Nicholas Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me,</hi> and Swore he would Run him thorow. Likewiſe <hi>Walter Campion</hi> (of whoſe prodigious Perjuries hereafter) a <hi>Blacksmith</hi> in <hi>Dadbrook,</hi> near <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> Seiſed a young man in the Street (who had been long Sick before, and had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a little ſtrength now to come Abroad) and commands him to go along with him; which he refuſing to do, he forcibly Drags him along; the other demanding a Warrant of him for ſo doing, he took a Piſtol out of his Pocket, and told him that was his <hi>Warrant,</hi> threatning no leſs than death to him. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them highly and terribly threatned a young Woman, bruiſing her Arms by a forcibly Hailing, and Pulling her along, whereby ſhe was much Affrighted, and whereof ſhe much complained. Theſe are ſome of their brutiſh Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſavage Actions at that time. After which, <hi>John Lucas</hi> (who was diſarm'd) to be reveng'd, accuſed ſeveral for beating him, whereof <hi>William Gilberd,</hi> of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> was one; accordingly a Warrant was granted by Mr. <hi>Hele,</hi> upon the Oath that the ſaid <hi>Lucas</hi> had taken, to Convene the ſaid <hi>W. G.</hi> before him; who when he appear'd in obedience to the ſame, <hi>Lucas</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged he was miſtaken, after he had thus ſworn againſt him. When the <hi>Seſſions</hi> came, <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> who was Bound over to them, makes his Appearance; but the Judg of the Seſſions, Mr. <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w,</hi> would take no notice of his Breaking the Peace, but ſhamefully Acquits him, Juſtifies him in what he did, highly Countenances him; the <hi>Clerk of the Peace</hi> refuſed to take any Fees of him, whereby all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement was given him, and the reſt of the Fraternity, outragiouſly to Abuſe at their will and pleaſure, ſuch as are called <hi>Conventiclers,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks;</hi> and though this was ſo <hi>Notorious</hi> a <hi>Riot,</hi> according to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> yet the leaſt Notice was not taken of it. Had a <hi>Heathen</hi> ſeen with what Partiality, and Favour towards one Party, all things were managed, and with great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, Injuſtice, and Cruelty towards the other (that is, thoſe whom <hi>Lucas</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53767:6"/> falſly accuſed for beating him; and one <hi>William March,</hi> as wrongfully, for ſpeaking ſome Seditious words, whom Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> would not give any time to provide Sureties for the good Behaviour, but Commanded with a moſt ſtern Countenance, and in a moſt wrathful manner, which ſhew'd how much his Heart was fill'd, and envenomed with Envy and Malice, the later preſently to take him) he muſt needs have Cry'd out, that certainly Chriſtianity Eradicates, and deſtroys common Equity. Here the very Scum of the Countrey, the moſt abject <hi>Fellows,</hi> and <hi>Droſs</hi> of Mankind, were by Mr. <hi>Carew,</hi> ſuffered to <hi>Taunt, Vilifie,</hi> and ſet at naught ſome Juſtices upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Hele,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> (being lookt upon as Favourits of <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and becauſe they would not Oppreſs their Neighbours; but more concerning them in the ſubſequent part of the <hi>Narrative</hi>) as if they had not been worthy to <hi>wipt</hi> their <hi>Shooes:</hi> No Check, or Controul was given them, but all was heard with much ſeeming de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and Complacency. Here every Informer was ſuffered to talk, as if he had been a Juſtice of Peace, or a Perſon of greateſt Honour. Among the reſt the <hi>Magnanimous Tom Ford,</hi> taking his place upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> aloud aſkt <hi>Lucas,</hi> if he wanted any Money, he ſhould have enough: And becauſe <hi>Lucas,</hi> after he had taken a poſitive <hi>Oath,</hi> that <hi>William Gilberd</hi> beat him, acknowledg'd his Errour. <hi>Tom Ford,</hi> in open Court, aloud, further told him (that he might be ſure not to Err the ſecond time) that if he that Beat him had Black Hair, then it was <hi>William Gilberd,</hi> but if he had Yellow Hair, it was <hi>Richerd</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as if Black and Yellow, put a Characteriſtical difference betwixt them, and all other men) whereupon <hi>Lucas</hi> at a venture, ſwore it was <hi>Richard</hi> that beat him, which was notoriouſly falſe; and this deſperate Oath was taken, and the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> was Bound over to two Aſſizes, of which there is yet a fuller Narrative to come.</p>
            <p>Two Lords-days more, <hi>viz. June</hi> the 19th. and 26th. theſe Informers hunt eagerly, but could find no Game, till <hi>July</hi> the 3d. when Mr. <hi>George Reynel</hi> was return'd into the Countrey, and then to work they go Early in the Mourning, having the freſh Scent of a <hi>Conventicle</hi> in their Noſes at <hi>Liuckham-hill-head,</hi> near <hi>Salcomb,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Malborough,</hi> thether therefore they repair with all the ſtrength they could make, being about Twenty, or Thirty Horſe and Foot, Arm'd, Swearing they would have <hi>Hicks</hi> if he were above ground: As they were going to the place, they overtook a Young-man of <hi>Kingsbridg;</hi> of whom Mr. <hi>Reynel,</hi> demanded where the Meeting was: He replied, He knew not (as he did not the particular place) and then leaves the Lane, to go into a Field<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which Mr. <hi>Reynel</hi> ſeeing, quickly Diſmounts, and ran after him; whom over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking (moſt well becoming a Juſtice of Peace) he Beat him with his Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whip, the Stripes whereof left their Marks and Prints behind them upon his Back, and Shouldiers. When they came near the place, where they ſuppoſed the Meeting was, they divided themſelves into two Squadrons, thinking by that means to Encompaſs the Miniſter, and People, and take them all in a Net at once, but when they came, they found only ſome few in the Circumjacent Fields; then they Rode fiercely about, being moſt Impetuous, and Eager in the Chaſe, and Purſuite of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> (though he had ſtolen neither Gold nor Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) Mr. <hi>Reynel</hi> offered Ten Pound, or a good Sum of Money to one man, if he would diſcover where he was, and demands of another to tell him, who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53767:6"/> being ſilent, he either ordered, or ſuffered one of his Attendants (I think his own Servant) to Beat him, which was Inhumanly done, with a Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel: Then meeting with a third Perſon, who upon demand, refuſed to make Diſcovery of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and being unwilling to go along with them, one of the Company (whether by the Order of the Juſtice, or no, I cannot certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell) Knockt him down, and then two of them, whereof the Perjured <hi>Companion</hi> was one; drag'd him along ſeveral Paces like a Dog, by the Heels, which put the man to great pain (he having not long before broke his Leg) which Extorted outerys, and complaints from him, a young <hi>Woman</hi> being near him, bid him be of good comfort, and not fear, for God would be with him (or words to that purpoſe) this <hi>wretched Champion</hi> hearing her ſay ſo, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to bring her into trouble: Saying to the Juſtice, <hi>Hark what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſaith?</hi> She ſaith the Devil is with us, and God is with them; but ſome of their own Company witneſſed the truth, and contradicted him: Then ſaith he, if ſhe ſaid not ſo, ſhe meant ſo. Then after they had ſpent two or three hours in making a diligent ſearch in Fields, Houſes (ſome whereof they vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently broke into, without demanding any entrance, or having a denial given them) Orchards, Gardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and had wearied out themſelves they depart; but Conviction was made of a Conventicle. Twenty Pound is Levied for Preaching, though it could never be proved; many did ſuffer, though they never knew their Accuſers, which is uſual; and commonly there is no other Evidence to ground, and bottome a Coviction upon, but what is given by Informers. And how Unreaſonable, Unwarrantable, and Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal this is, let all Engliſhmen, yea, and the world judg, ſeeing they are Parties ſo much concerned.</p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> (the Head of the Informers) expects ſome conſiderable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his good Service done his Majeſty, and the Church, as he accounts it, he writes therefore to the Biſhop of <hi>Exon</hi> (as he had done ſometimes before, declaring his ſeveral Services for the Church, his Endeavour to bring to Condigne puniſhment all di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enters from her) to acquaint him he had now done what he could in that ſingle <hi>Capacity</hi> he was in, hoping to arrive at ſome higher pitch of Honour; the <hi>Merit</hi> of his <hi>Zeal,</hi> and illuſtrious Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in his own eſteem, challenging no leſs than the reward of being made a <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> Which if he were inveſted with the Authority of, he promiſeth him with what Vigour, and Activity, he would Ruine, or Reduce to due Obedience, the Churches Enemies. The Biſhop perceiving him to be a Prompt and Active <hi>Young</hi> man, to promote the <hi>Hierarchical</hi> Intereſt, and having had Ample experience of his ſcorning to ſtick at the breaking of any Law, or committing the ſouleſt Riots to advance the ſame. He had no reaſon to ſuſpect his <hi>Cowardiſe,</hi> if he could get him Advanc'd to a Juſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in adventuring <hi>Soul, Body, Conſcience, Eſtate</hi> and all, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof. He therefore beſtirs himſelf to get him into the Commiſſion of Peace, which after much difficulty by the Arch-Biſhop, and the Earl of <hi>Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he effected. One might indeed have thought, that in good time there would have been a probability of his Advencement to the <hi>Degree</hi> of a <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,</hi> or <hi>Head Conſtable,</hi> but few or none judg'd him worthy of a higher Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, conſidering the Inferiority of his Quality, the Inconſiderableneſs of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53767:7"/> his Eſtate, being as his Neighbours (that know it well) affirm, at the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt but 200 Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> out of which he pays his <hi>Father,</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>George,</hi> and two Siſters, ſuch Annuities, that he cannot have much more than 60 pound <hi>per annum</hi> to maintain, and ſupport the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of a Juſtice. Its known likewiſe he is Indebted, being a Borrower of Money; How fit is he for his preſent Preferment, and capable of ſuch an Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſouls judg? I know no other reaſon why his <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Juſtices</hi> ſo much ſcorn and diſdain him, why none of them, nor any other <hi>Gentleman</hi> at the chief <hi>Sheriffs</hi> Table the laſt <hi>Aſſizes,</hi> thought him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be Drunk to; which was but <hi>ſower</hi> Sauce, I believe, to his ſweet Meat, and enough to hinder the good Concoction thereof, But however, though he that was ſo lately the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Informers,</hi> be now lookt upon but as the <hi>Tail</hi> of <hi>Juſtices,</hi> yet he is reſolved to make his Neighbours, and the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> to know his Authority; forthwith therefore he begins to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play its powerful Beams, the ſcorching Heat whereof, he makes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticlers ſufficiently to feel, but <hi>Excentrick</hi> to all Law, as the following In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances will moſt clearly Demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>To begin then with his firſt Conviction of a Conventicle held at <hi>Linckham-Hill-Head,</hi> the 26th. of <hi>July,</hi> 1670. which he expreſt in his Warrant to the Conſtables for Diſtreſs, was grounded upon the Oaths of two or more Witneſſes, but who theſe were is unknown; no Perſon being Convicted in the preſence of his Accuſers, nor Summoned to appear before his Worſhip, to hear what was Evidenced againſt them, or what they could plead for themſelves, till the Warrants were granted for Levying Fines, to the Value of Twenty Four Pounds Ten Shillings, upon ſix Perſons by Diſtreſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making Demand of the Money. Beſides ſeveral other Diſtreſſes, that I forbear to mention, which the Sufferers groan under, they being ſo Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and their Goods ſold ſo much under Value. Alſo, they were able to prove themſelves elſewhere the 26th. of <hi>July,</hi> which when Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, he gave the Conſtables new Warrants to keep the above-mention'd Sums for the 3d. of <hi>July,</hi> commanding them to return the Money to ſome whoſe Goods they had taken, and under-ſold: The Conſtables therefore of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> bring to Mr. <hi>John Hingſton,</hi> Seven Pound Ten Shills, which was Levied on him: He told them they had no Money, but Goods from him, which if they would bring back again, its likely he might receive them; whereon one of the Conſtables threw down the Money on his Table, and the other catcht it up by a ſecond Warrant, he not receiving it, and the firſt Warrants Mr. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</hi> hath ſince forced from the Conſtables.</p>
            <p>Another Conviction of his was as followeth: Mr. <hi>Tooker,</hi> a Non-conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſter, living in the Pariſh of <hi>Weſt-Altington,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> having three Gentle-women at his Houſe on a Sabbath-day (who viſited his Wife, being much afflicted for the death, by drowning at Sea, of her Son and only Child) Prayed with them, it being in the Afternoon when there was no Miniſter at the Pariſh Church; and while he was engag'd in this Chriſtian Work, and Duty, come <hi>Lucas, Campion Arnel,</hi> with <hi>Leech</hi> (the Apoſtate, and <hi>Judas</hi>) all of the Informing Crew, with ſome others, and beſet the Houſe, to ſee that none ſhould paſs in or out, while they ſent
<pb facs="tcp:53767:7"/> for the Conſtables, and Church-wardens of the Pariſh, before whoſe coming, one of the Gentle-womens Servants came with a Horſe to carry her home, but ſeeing the Houſe beſet returned again immediately; and when they came, the Doors were preſently opened to them, who entring the Houſe made a general ſearch, the Informers aſſiſting them, but found not one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon beſides the three aforeſaid <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> and the Family; this highly diſcontents, and enrugeth the Informers, becauſe they miſled of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Prize, and Prey. However, they ſaid, this ſhould not ſerve their turn, but they would make a Conventicle of the three Gentle-womens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there: Accordingly they immediately repaired to the <hi>New Informing Juſtice</hi> Bear, and acquainted him; that though there were but three Perſons in the Houſe beſides the Family, yet there was a Servant of one of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-womens, who came Riding thether, and Mr. <hi>Revil Baſtard</hi> (who hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Informers were there, came to the Houſe to ſee what they did, although not until the Officers had ſearcht the Houſe and were gone) with <hi>Joſeph Tripe,</hi> who was then walking in his own Ground, where it was not poſſible for him to hear any thing that was ſpoken in the Houſe, and the Informers were betwixt him and the Houſe likewiſe, and this Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> judg'd to be <hi>Notorious Evidence,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of <hi>Fact</hi> ſufficient to make it a Conventicle; and accordingly the next Morning (without ſending for any of the Perſons complain'd of, to hear what they could ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) grants his Warrants for Diſtraining of Mr. <hi>Tooker</hi> for 30 Pound, and <hi>Joſeph Tripe</hi> for 10 Pound; the Officers of the Pariſh the ſame day, came to Mr. <hi>Tookers</hi> Houſe, and the Informers with them, without being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or commanded, who pulled and Tore down all the Goods in his Houſe; and ſuch was the Inmanity, and Inhumanity of theſe <hi>Rapacious Harpies,</hi> and Voracious Birds of Prey (I mean the Informers) that they did not only Seiſe his Beds, and Bedclothes, but the poor Childrens Wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-clothes, and the very Victuals that was in the Houſe, they left no Corner or Place they could find unſearcht, for Money; neither his Pockets, nor the Fleſh-Tubs, Pigs-pailes, all ſorts of Bottles, nor yet the very Cloſe-ſtool (as if the evacuated Excrements of <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> could be converted into Coin, or were rich Bullion, however theſe <hi>New-Gold-Finders</hi> judg'd that ſomething more precious, and Odoreferous a <hi>Partepoſt</hi> might drop from them, than other perſons) ten Shillings they ſtole, but who was the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon that did it, I know not; but this I know, that one of the principal <hi>Actors</hi> among them was <hi>John Bear,</hi> or <hi>Beer</hi> (who by a Nick-name is called <hi>Cocky Bear</hi> in the Countrey) a Couſin of the New Juſtices, that had ſufficienly experienced the Pinches of Poverty, before he took up this moſt Diſgraceful, Informing Trade, and now he with the reſt, live upon the Spoyl of the Contrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſep Tripe,</hi> having his Goods deſtrain'd, immediately repairs to Juſtice <hi>Bear,</hi> and acquaints him that he was ſo far from coming to Mr. <hi>Tookers</hi> Houſe, as that he ſhund and eſtranged himſelf from it (there being a Sute in Law betwixt him, and Mr. <hi>Tooker,</hi> upon her former Husbands account) and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prov'd, that he was within his Houſe all that day, until that time that the Informers came, Mr. <hi>Bevil Baſtard,</hi> and the Gentle-womans Servant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53767:8"/> prove the ſame; upon which, Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> diſmiſt them, and ſet their Goods a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Liberty (Mr. <hi>Tookers</hi> being much Spoiled, and Damnified) but he had not his Money again, which was ſtolen from him; and becauſe Mr. <hi>Tooker,</hi> about half a year after, complained of the dammage done to his Goods, and that he had reaſon to have Satisfaction for it; Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> grants a new Warrant to Seiſe all his Goods, and in caſe no Goods could be found, then to Apprehend his Perſon; which Neceſſitates, and Enforceth Mr. <hi>Tooker</hi> to Diſperſe his Family, and betake himſelf to a Wandring Life, to avoid his <hi>Impla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able</hi> Wrath and Malice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the 11th. This <hi>Gorings Crew,</hi> or <hi>Plunderers,</hi> went to Mr. <hi>Burd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods</hi> Houſe (a Non-conformiſt) in the Pariſh of <hi>Malborough,</hi> where they found him ſinging a Pſalm with four of his Neigbours, beſides his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and having a <hi>Maſtiff</hi>-Dog without at the Door, he Barks at them, a Girle living near, perceiving this, ſets on the Dog (it's likely underſtanding that though theſe were not of the ſame Species, or Kind with the Dog, yet that they were of the ſame Diſpoſition) which the People of the Houſe hearing, preſently call off, and opening the Door to let him in, the Girl being affrighted, enters in too, and the Informers with her, even upon her Heels; and this Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> makes a ſufficient Ground and Reaſon, to proceed on to a Conviction of a <hi>Conventicle</hi> (notwithſtanding that one of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers did acknowledg, that the Girl went in when the Door was opened, to the Dog) he Levieth therefore Twenty Pound upon Mr. <hi>Burdwood</hi> for his Houſe, Twenty Pound more for Preaching, and Five Shillings for each of the reſt. One <hi>Chiſwel</hi> of <hi>Kingsbridg, Black-ſmith,</hi> owing Mr. <hi>Burdwood</hi> Three Pound, had a Warrant ſent him from this <hi>New Juſtice,</hi> requiring him to detain the Money in his hand, which he through fear did; another War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant he ſent to the Conſtables of <hi>Cornwoody,</hi> for the Seiſing of an Eſtate which Mr. <hi>Bardwood</hi> had there, if they found it Chattel for Lives, or Years. <hi>April</hi> the 23d. of this preſent Year, <hi>Leech</hi> (the <hi>Judas</hi>) and <hi>Arnel</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Informer (two expert and conſiderable <hi>Setting Dogs,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> is the Maſter of) Hunt about the Countrey for Game, both for their Maſter, and themſelves, and at laſt they came to a Farmers houſe, in a Village cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Leigh,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Modbury,</hi> about Five or Six Miles diſtant, from the place where they live; and ſeeing ſome perſons paſs into the Farmers Yard (it being the Forenoon) one of them ſtops at the Houſe to watch, the other went to call the Officers of the Pariſh, who came with all poſſible ſpeed to the Houſe, and narrowly Searcht it, but found not one perſon in the Houſe, or about it, beſides the Family belonging to it (and the truth is, the people only paſſed through the Court, and went to ſome other place, or about their Occaſions elſewhere, while the Farmer was Praying with his Family) Nevertheleſs, the Conſciences of theſe Informers were ſo prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly Debaucht, and Cauteriz'd, that they took their Oaths before Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bruton,</hi> that they ſaw a great number of perſons go into the Houſe, and that there was at that time a great Number there. Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> who called his Neighbour Juſtice <hi>Bruton,</hi> to aſſiſt him (one ready enough for ſuch an undertaking; which makes the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in thoſe parts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beholden to the rude Bayliffs.)</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53767:8"/>
            <p>Goes out of his own Diviſion to Execute the Law; comes therefore to <hi>Mudbury</hi> a day or two after, and makes a Warrant to this purpoſe, <hi>That whereas they are</hi> Credibly Informed, <hi>that now there is a</hi> Conventicle <hi>at ſuch a place, theſe are therefore,</hi> &amp;c. The Informers accompany the Officers to the Farmers houſe (this Lye being forg'd and fram'd to attain their end) and violently Break open the Doors (there not being one perſon within) and enters the Houſe, which when they had done, the Informers ſhew'd the Officers another Warrent immediately to take Diſtreſs; to work therefore they go, and empty the mans Houſe of all his Goods, leaving him neither Bed, Pot, nor Pan, Diſh nor Spoon; they took away his Sider, and ſold it for about Four Shillings a Hogs-head (as they did all other things at an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Value) and I hear likewiſe his very <hi>Fewel,</hi> which was for the Twenty Pound that was Levied upon him, by which the poor man is almoſt, if not utterly undone. Should I write all the unjuſt, and Illegal Actings of this (by an <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiphraſis</hi>) Juſtice <hi>Bear,</hi> it would make theſe few Sheets ſwell to a conſiderable Volumn: However I will Epitomize a few more before I have finiſhed this Narrative, and bring them within as narrow a Compaſs as I can, that it may be known how much his Majeſty is abus'd, and diſhonour'd by ſuch Oppreſſing, and <hi>empty</hi> Perſons; who only Proſtitute Authority to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and Gratifie a ſingle particular <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which will be found too narrow a Baſis for our vaſt Structure, and too weak a Leg for our great and <hi>Bulky Body Politick,</hi> to ſtand long upon.</p>
            <p>I have in the preceding part of this Narrative, told the Reader of Fifteen Informers (or very near the Number) who as <hi>Volunteers,</hi> Invaded, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet in a moſt Hoſtile manner Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe at <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> the 12th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1670. Among whom, there was one <hi>John Lucas,</hi> who ſtood at the Back-door with a Piſtol, threatning to Kill any that come out, which was the cauſe why he was Diſarmed, being bound before to the Peace, or good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and deporting himſelf ſo Minaciouſly, without any Authority. This <hi>Lucas,</hi> in the Month of <hi>December</hi> laſt Sickned, and Died the beginning of <hi>January;</hi> when he was Dead, his Informing Brethren Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> and the reſt, threaten that ſome ſhould ſuffer for Murdering him. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> leaves the Countrey about Eighteen Weeks, and near the time that the ſaid <hi>Lucas</hi> died, his Adverſaries conjectur'd, he was returned in <hi>Devon.</hi> They reſolved to make him guilty of this horrid Murder, as they reported it to be (though while <hi>Lucas</hi> was well, and in health, he never Accuſed him for Beating, or Aſſaulting him at the time ſpoken of, or any time after) <hi>Juſtice Bear</hi> being return'd from the <hi>Seſſions,</hi> preſently enquires into the pretended bloody Fact. <hi>Lucas</hi> his <hi>Widdow,</hi> ſhe ſwears before him (who was then the Head of this Informing party) that when he lay upon his Sick-bed, he ſaid that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> came out in the Head of Threeſcore men (or near that Number) and Knockt him down, and that Eight perſons more, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Bevil Baſtard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Henry Luke, William</hi> and <hi>Richard Gilberd, — Merrigame, J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn Leech, Nicholas Hexome,</hi> and <hi>John Bowen,</hi> fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and Beat him ſo cruelly, than he was never well after, but gradually Languiſht, which was the cauſe of his Sickneſs, and ſo of his Death; her Father <hi>Kiſland</hi> (a Fellow that <hi>Lucas</hi> was heard to ſay, not long before he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53767:9"/> fell ſick, would for a Groat betray, or take away any mans Life, or words to that purpoſe) Swears that when he was ſtript, there were the Impreſſions of the Blows, which he called <hi>Stripes,</hi> upon his Back; this being done, Juſtice <hi>Bear</hi> grants forth his Warrants to Apprehend all theſe Perſons upon Suſpition of Murder; they all yield themſelves, but Mr. <hi>H.</hi> (who was not at home, nor hath been for many Months) Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> refuſed to Bayl them, though the Caſe will admit thereof, to the Goal therefore they muſt go; the <hi>Mittimuſſes</hi> of ſome of them were made, but two other <hi>Juſtices</hi> did Bayl them, either not being ſo <hi>Ignorant</hi> of the Law, or not ſo <hi>Malicious</hi> as himſelf, Now though this Juſtice and the reſt of the Informers confidently Report, and Aſſert, that this was a moſt <hi>Bloody,</hi> and <hi>Barbarous</hi> Murder, yet they Bury him, never endeavouring, and it's likely never intending, to have him Crown'd; a Coroner indeed came not long after, but did not his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (I will not confidently avere that Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> or any other, did tamper with him privately to be gone, knowing that no Stripes would be found upon his Back.) But the Accuſed knowing their own pure, and ſpotleſs Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, were reſolv'd to have him Crown'd, and accordingly ſent for a Coroner, who came and Executed his Office according to Law. When his Jury was Impanel'd witneſſes on both ſides, with Impartiality were Examined. <hi>Lucas</hi> his Widdow, and her Father ſwore as before the Juſtice (except as ſome ſay ſhe accuſed not Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) to whom was added a new Witneſs, <hi>John Bear</hi> (a Fellow that not long before took an Oath before a Juſtice of Peace, that Mr. <hi>John Tripe</hi> of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> was at a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> when he was ſick at home) who ſwore that going with <hi>Lucas</hi> to find a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> he Riding and the other walking on Foot; and not holding pace with him, he aſked him the reaſon why he could go no faſter. To whom he replied: He was never well ſince he was Beaten at Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe. After the Evidence of theſe three was taken, then were Witneſſes for the <hi>Accuſed</hi> Examined; who were firſt his own Natural Parents, its well known in the Countrey where they Live, that there was much Love betwixt theſe and their Son, that he was very dear to them; inſomuch that his Affectionate Mother, from the Intenſneſs and Strength of her Love, when her Son was taken out of the Grave, after he had putrified there a full Fortnight, Embrac'd him (as if by her own warm Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſhe would have Reanimated, or given him a ſecond Life, or breath'd her own into him; yea, ſhe abundantly wept over him, as if with a Flood of her own <hi>Tears,</hi> ſhe would have waſht away the Filth, and Corruption of his Body) Certainly then if they had Apprehended, or Suſpected theſe Perſons, or any other to have ſhed his Blood, they could not have been back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to proſecute them; but they being convinc't of the contrary, they Voluntarily take their <hi>Oaths</hi> that to their Apprehenſion, their Son was us Healthful, Strong, and Lively from the 12th. of <hi>June,</hi> to the time he ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as ever they knew him, that they never heard him complain of any of the Accuſed doing him wrong, or hurt: They further Sware, that all the time of his Sickneſs, they never heard any complaint of this Nature, and that they did believe in their Conſciences he had no wrong, or harm done him by the Perſons Accuſed; and for the Stripes upon his Back that <hi>Kelland</hi> ſware to, they did judg them nothing but Strikes made with the folding of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53767:9"/> Shirt, and Waſt-coat, lying much upon his Back. Another Witneſs was his <hi>Phiſitian,</hi> who Atteſted upon Oath, that he died of a Putrid Feaver. A third that gave Evidence, was a Fellow-workman with him, who did Swear that the next day after this pretended Beating was, he came to work with him, and he aſked him if he was Hurt by Beating the day before? and he anſwered, No; And further he Witneſſed, that he wrought with him Seven Weeks together, and that all the time he did his Work (being a <hi>Carpenter</hi>) as Luſtily, and Lively, as ever he knew him to perform it. <hi>William March</hi> (who is lately Dead, but while he Liv'd, was known, and approved to be an Honeſt man, and Peaceable man, by all his Neighbours) had not Providence prevented his coming, would as he intended, have taken his Oath, that he, being next Neighbour to <hi>Lucas,</hi> heard him the Evening of the ſame Day in which it's ſaid he was Beaten, ſpeak theſe words, as he was walking in his Garden with another man: <hi>That he had no more hurt than himſelf;</hi> when he aſked him the Queſtion, whether or no, he was ſo Beaten. And further told him, They did, or might Strike one another; but they could not Strike him they ſtood ſo thick: This, <hi>William March</hi> often while he Lived, affirm'd to be a Truth; but though he was now wanting to give in ſuch material Evidence. Yet the former with <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary Cawſeys,</hi> who (being Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his next Neighbour) was in her own Court, or Garden, a Spectator at that time, was ſo Pertinent, Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and Satisfactory, that there was no need of any more.</p>
            <p>Evidence therefore being thus given on both ſides, the Jury Adviſe, and Conſult together, what Verdict to bring in; the far greater part preſently concurred in their Judgments, that <hi>Lucas</hi> died a Natural Death; Three or Four diſſented from the reſt, which cauſed a Debate, and Things to be Argued <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> ſeveral Hours: Then one Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> (who hath good Judgment and Skill in <hi>Chirurgery</hi>) being a Juror, declared his Opinion; That if <hi>Lucas</hi> had Sickned, and Died of any Blows that was given him ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they muſt have Impoſtumated before that time, and this gave general Satisfaction: So the <hi>Verdict</hi> of the Jury was, that he died a Natural death, by the <hi>Viſitation</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this Search is not only the Mortal, but Immortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and malice of this Juſtice <hi>Bear</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> That about three Weeks after he grants forth a <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry,</hi> to purſue him for Wilful murder; when his <hi>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> fury could not reach him any other way: And though by Vertue of his Warrants, his Houſe had been Searcht for him ſeveral times before, yet now he is reſolved to make thorow work (ſuppoſing him to be in that Countrey, when he was not) on a <hi>Saturday</hi> Night therefore about Ten a Clock, came the Conſtables of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> with moſt of the Informers for their Guard, and many others, to the Number of near Thirty Perſons, and Beſets his Houſe; to whom his Wife opened the Doors, a ſtrict Search then they make for him: One of the Conſtables commanded to Stab any that ſhould go out (a Fellow lately put into that Office by Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> who was never iudg'd fit for it, or capable of it before) but not finding him there, they made a further Search, very diligently all that Night in the Town, diſturbing many Families; and among the reſt, they re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uire ſome <hi>Quakers</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53767:10"/> to open their Doors (though no doubt they expected him not to be ſhelter'd in their Houſes, as the Sequel declares, from whom he had met with ſo much Diſturbance, and Oppoſition in Preaching) and when they were got in, they violently took away their Goods. The Sabbath-day in the Morning early, they leave <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> and go to <hi>Weſtalvington,</hi> where a Search was made in ſome Gentlemens Houſes, but to no purpoſe; from thence they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Milton</hi> Pariſh, from it to <hi>Hughes,</hi> ſo to <hi>Salcomb,</hi> thus they ſpent the Sabbath: And after they had by their great Labouriouſneſs, and Diligence tyred themſelves, they gave over, not finding their Prey, having Searcht near Thirty Houſes: How unwearied, and implacable is Malice, how ſweet is Revenge?</p>
            <p>When the Aſſizes begun at <hi>Exon,</hi> the eight Perſons ſpoken of before, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Recognizance, made their Appearance, and the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> debated the finding of the <hi>Bill</hi> of Murder againſt them, which continued from <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> or <hi>Thurſday,</hi> till <hi>Munday</hi> (when the Aſſizes were nearly concluded) the Gentlemen being divided Thirteen againſt Twelve; the greater Number were for finding it an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> but the Twelve were for finding <hi>Billa Vera.</hi> Now the Reaſon why there was ſuch a Number for it, was in all probability ſome Under-hand dealing with the Under-Sheriff, Mr. <hi>Norman</hi> in <hi>Exon;</hi> for Sir <hi>John Davy,</hi> the chief Sheriff of the County, had ſent a Liſt of ſuch Gentlemen to Mr. <hi>Norman,</hi> as he deſir'd the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> ſhould conſiſt of, with Orders to warn them; but he not liking what his Maſter had done; without acquainting him with it, takes upon him to alter his Liſt, leaving out whom he pleaſed, and warning ſuch in their ſtead as he judg'd more fit, and ſuch as he knew would gratifie the Malice of the others, whatever it did his own. Notwithſtanding therefore, all the care of that Honourable Perſon Sir <hi>John Davy,</hi> to have a <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> in reference to all Concernments that ſhould come under their Cognizance, of Sober, Solid, Judicious, and Honeſt Gentlemen; it was now in a great meaſure other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Conſtituted, there being thoſe that without any reſpect to Equity, and Juſtice, would take away the Lives of thoſe called <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> The <hi>Bill</hi> being now found, the Priſoners were called to the <hi>Bar,</hi> where they Pleaded not Guilty, and then came to their Tryal, which laſted about three Hours; in reference to which, I ſhall give an Account both of the prodigious Perjuries of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes for the King, and the Partiality (to give it no worſe Name) of the Judg, before whom the Tryal was.</p>
            <p>And while I preſent to the Reader ſome of thoſe <hi>Sowre Grapes,</hi> which theſe Plants ſo far <hi>Degenerated</hi> from all Truth, and Righteouſneſs, brought forth; I ſhall begin with Mr. <hi>John Bear,</hi> the Juſtice, who being called to be a Witneſs againſt the Priſoners, Swore as if he had no Senſe of an Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Deity, or a <hi>Divine Nemeſis,</hi> to take Vengeance upon him, for his unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled <hi>Perjuries.</hi> The Sum and Subſtance of his falſe Oath, is, That <hi>Lucas</hi> was almoſt Beaten into the Ground, that the Priſoners did lye upon him, and Beating him, had made a Pit in the Ground, enough to bury him in, (which muſt be very large conſidering his great Dimenſions, but its likely this Gentleman was reſolved to Swear <hi>Rhetorically,</hi> by an <hi>Hyperbole</hi>) when the Ground the Pit was made in, was only a very ſoft Dunghil, and many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53767:10"/> People paſſing over it, at that time, had Trod it down, and made ſome Holes, or Pits in it; at this deſperate rate he went on Swearing Roundly, and Smoothly, but with ſuch a ſtill and low Voice, that the Priſoners at the <hi>Bar,</hi> could not diſtinctly hear him: Therefore Mr. <hi>Luke,</hi> humbly deſired the Judg, that he would command him to ſpeak more Audibly, which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſo Juſt and Reaſonable a Requeſt, was granted; in obedience to the Judg, he raiſed his Voice a degree higher, but yet not Loud enough to be heard by the Priſoners (from all probability he was unwilling they ſhould hear him, that they might not except againſt any thing he Swore, and ſo all might be credited by the Jury, and likewiſe his Conſcience might fly in his Face, and tell him what monſtruous falſhoood he did atteſt) Mr. <hi>Luke</hi> therefore moved again, that he might more extend his Voice: Which at laſt doing, he deſired the Judg to ask him; Whether he ſwore thoſe things from his own knowledg? The Queſtion being aſkt him, he replied No, but he was informed of it, and had heard ſo. Now he was pincht to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for if he had anſwered Affirmatively, there were thoſe preſent (which he was not ignorant of) that could prove the contrary, he not coming till after <hi>Lucas</hi> was diſarmed, and upon his Legs, and when there was no perſon in the leaſt that did moleſt him. How may the Reader ſee what bloody Malice, Prompted, and Acted, this <hi>Juſtice Bear,</hi> to precipitate, and hurry himſelf into the abſorping <hi>Gulph</hi> of Perjury. For ſuppoſing all had been Truth which he Swore, yet it's Falſe-ſwearing in the ſight of God, to Swear what he had no certain knowledg of, (ſuch knowledg being an Eſſential Conſtitution of a right Oath, as the Divine Oracles, and Caſuiſts do Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine) and it's very probable, he contracted more of this dreadful Guilt upon his Soul: For he further Swore, that a little before <hi>Lucas</hi> his Death, he was with him, and that then he heard him charge his Death among others, upon <hi>William Gilberd;</hi> and yet afterwards, when the Queſtion was aſked him, Whether <hi>Lucas</hi> did not Acquit the ſaid <hi>W. G.</hi> before Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> (then one of his Majeſties Juſtices) after he had Accuſed him upon Oath, for Beating him, he confeſt he did; it being ſo known a Truth, he could not deny it. Let the Impartial Reader judg, that rationally it muſt be diſſonant from Truth, that <hi>L.</hi> who had Acquitted <hi>J.</hi> before a Juſtice of Peace, would ſo long after, charge his Death upon him: And though Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> ſwore he did it upon all the reſt, yet this having the ugly Viſage of a Lye, what may we judg of the whole, but that it was a Contexture, and <hi>Concatenation</hi> of many notorious Falſhoods together. Now we will leave Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> Immerſt, and Drown'd in the dreadful Guilt of his Perjuries (though afterwards we ſhall find him ſinking deeper) and proceed to another deſperate Swearer, by Name <hi>John Roope,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Cheſtow:</hi> He Swore, that when he came he found <hi>Lucas</hi> lying upon his Back in a Wet, or Dirty place, and <hi>John Leech,</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xome</hi> upon him; and that <hi>Lucas</hi> was ſo weak, and Spent, when they roſe from him, that he had not ſtrength of himſelf to riſe, but was help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or liſted up by him: But <hi>Barbary Cawſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> witneſſeth (who was a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, ſtanding upon the Hedg that parts betwixt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Garden, and here, under which <hi>Lucas</hi> was thrown down, and lay at that time when <hi>R.</hi> came, ſo that ſhe had him full, and perfectly in her View) that its true
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53767:11"/> 
               <hi>J. R.</hi> coming immediately as <hi>H.</hi> ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from <hi>L.</hi> he took him by the Arm, but by his own ſtrength, with much Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bleneſs, and Quickneſs, he Leaped, or Sprung (but was not Pull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d) up, and threw his Arms about him, crying out with great Vehemency, and Voceferations, There's the Rogue (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>H.</hi>) that took away the Piſtol; and to give a clear Demonſtration, that he was not ſo ſpent, with great Force and Fury (Mr. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</hi> with ſome other Informers, being then in ſight for his encouragement) fell upon <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xome,</hi> wrapping one hand in his Hair behind, and pulling back his Head with the other hand, gave him ſuch a Blow upon the Mouth, that he ſtruck him down to the Ground, where he lay a conſiderable time before he could riſe, being depriv'd of his Senſes by the force, and greatneſs of the Blow.</p>
            <p>The next Witneſs againſt the Priſoners, that I ſhall give the Reader a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Account of, is, <hi>Walter Campion,</hi> (who bears the Bell away from all the reſt of his Perjur'd Brethren, being a moſt profound Sink of Lies, and Abyſs of Falſhoods, to whom the precedency of all the Knights of Poſt is due) who Sware he ſaw the print of Forty ſtrokes in the pilm upon his Back. <hi>Roope</hi> ſwore, he hearing a great Tumult in Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Court, haſted with all ſpeed thither (and it was no great diſtance from him) where he found <hi>Lucas</hi> down upon the Ground, and lying upon his Back, but ſaw no man ſtrike him; it's ſtrange then that he ſhould have ſo many Blows given him, in ſo ſhort a time, and that in a Throng, and Crowd, where one hinder an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other (as <hi>William March</hi> heard <hi>L.</hi> ſay in his own Garden, they could not ſtrike him, they ſtood ſo thick) he could not have them when he was thrown down, becauſe he lay upon his Back, as <hi>J. R.</hi> ſwears; and it's ſtrange he ſhould receive ſo many behind, and not one before that did appear, or was ſpoken of; either they were moſt baſe Cowards, that would only Aſſault him behind, or he was a notorious Coward that would not face about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf. But any Impartial Reader may ſee by this, if no more ſhould be produced to Demonſtrate it; What a <hi>Diſperado</hi> this <hi>Campion</hi> is for Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? But to evince this Perjury more clearly, let it be conſidered what <hi>J. R.</hi> Swore, <hi>viz.</hi> That he found <hi>Lucas</hi> upon his Back, in a Wet or Durty place (which is a truth, for there many times Water runs, and there is always Mud and Durt) the Forty blows then that <hi>C.</hi> ſwore he ſaw, muſt be either before he fell, or after; before it could not be, becauſe he was thrown down before <hi>R.</hi> came, who came before <hi>Campion;</hi> after, no man can ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuppoſe it to be, becauſe he lying in a Wet place upon his Back, the Pilm, or Duſt muſt be removed, or changed into Durt, ſo that no Prints, or Impreſſions of Blows could be ſeen in it; yea, if it had been in a Dry blace he fell in, yet Tumbling, and Strugling upon his Back, would have defaced them altogether, or rendred them very undiſtinguiſhable; it's ſtrange fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo many Blows ſhould be unobſerved by all the reſt, as if he who had a more notorious <hi>Lying</hi> Tongue, ſhould have a more quick and piercing <hi>Eye,</hi> than all his Brethren had. And take all this in Conjunction with what <hi>Barbary Cawſey</hi> ſwore, that ſhe was a Spectator, and Obſerver of all Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges both at the beginning, and the end, and ſaw not one Blow given him; and that ſhe heard the people, or ſome among them ſay; Strike him not a Blow: And then the incedibility of all that he Swore in reference to this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53767:11"/> particular will be moſt manifeſt. So I will leave this, and proceed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther piece of Perjury as Infernal, and Tremendous, as the former, that he was Guilty of in the open Court, where he Swore twice (to render Mr. <hi>H.</hi> as oudious as he could) once when he was call'd to be a Witneſs againſt Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baſtard,</hi> for neglecting their Duty as Juſtices, in the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Act againſt Conventicles; and now when he was a Witneſs againſt the Priſoners, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>H.</hi> near the time that the Act againſt Conventicles was in Force, threatned, that if any man came to Diſturb him in keeping them, he would Knock him down, ſhewing him a <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as he term'd it, near as thick as the wreſt of his Arm; to whom, <hi>Campion</hi> ſaid, he Reply'd, You may miſs your blow, and if I cloſe with you, I may prove as nimble as you (or words to that purpoſe) and further ſaid, he was not affraid of him: To whom Mr. <hi>H.</hi> replied after this manner, Sav'ſt thou ſo, and pulling out of his Pocket a <hi>Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etto,</hi> or long Daggar Knife, turn'd the point of it towards him, and told him, there was that which ſhould pick his Teeth. That the Reader may know the matchleſs Empudence of this Fellow, and what a Debaucht, Profligated, and Canterized Conſcience he hath, which Generates his moſt Horrid, and Helliſh Perjuries, I will give him a True, and Faithful Relation of this Matter; as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> calls the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Hearts to Witneſs, and <hi>Verbo ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erdotis,</hi> doth proſeſs. Which take as followeth:</p>
            <p>About the midſt of <hi>December,</hi> 1669. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> had a Horſe dangerouſly wounded, and employed <hi>Campion</hi> to cure him, who came to his Houſe to dreſs him; and one Evening before he went away, he aſked him if he would Drink, which <hi>Campion</hi> accepted of: He then put it to his choice, whether he would drink Beer, or Sider. <hi>Campion</hi> replied; He could drink Beer at home, and he knew Mr. <hi>H.</hi> had good Sider, therefore he would rather chuſe that; which when he had drunk, he commended it. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> at that time had a <hi>Staff</hi> in Hand, which <hi>Campion</hi> took notice of, and ſaid, it was a good one: To whom he replied; That he had rather have ſuch a Staft, than a ſmall Rapier, ſuch as now was in uſe. Then ſaid <hi>Campion,</hi> But what if one ſhould give you a prick? Mr. <hi>H.</hi> again: Poſſibly he might put by one thruſt, which if he did, he would prevent the ſecond, if he got one blow at his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary that ſhould Aſſault him. <hi>Campion</hi> ſpeaking of his Skill in Fencing, and what Feats he could do with a Sword: Mr. <hi>H.</hi> told him (which was the Concluſion of the Diſcourſe) that if a man ſhould Aſſault him with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, he would be in ſuch a poſture with his Knife in his left Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking it then out of his Pocket) and his Staff in his Right; and if he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by a Thruſt, he would quickly pick his Teeth. This Knife is indeed made after the form of a Daggar, with a little Croſs-bar, to prevent its run<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h the Sheath; both Haſt and Blade, are but about a quarter of a Yard lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And when Mr. <hi>H.</hi> firſt had it, they were frequently, and commonly u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d for cutting Meat, and for this purpoſe many Sober perſons uſe them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et: But in all this Diſcourſe, there was not one word relating to C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icles, or in the leaſt bordering upon them, it being at that time when to Act was in Force againſt them, and ſeveral Months before the preſent Act was made; and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> never exchang done word with <hi>Campion,</hi> by way of any Diſcourſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53767:12"/> ſince he pay'd his Money for the Cure he wrought, which was a few days after it was done. And now I ſhall leave this Fellow a while, deeply Abyſt in his Perjuries, and under the heavy Preſſures of that Soul-ſinking Guilt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Ford</hi> (that man of Magnanimity, and Might, already mentioned) Sware that <hi>Lucas</hi> was thrown down on his Back athwart a Gutter, which was pitcht with ſharp ſtones, over which, by the Head and Heels, they drew his Body. Now that the <hi>Reader</hi> may underſtand what a Brother in Iniquity this man is with the other, he muſt caſt his Eye upon what followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Tho. Ford</hi> was not there when <hi>Lucas</hi> was thrown down, and diſarm'd, neither ſaw he in what poſture he lay. He Swore further, that Mr. <hi>Bevil Baſtard,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Luke,</hi> cry'd, Kill the Rogue, Knock down the Rogue, and yet he was not there (as before is aſſerted, and can be prov'd) when <hi>Lucas</hi> in ſtrugling for the Piſtol fell, or was thrown upon the Ground; and none can prove, or doth affirm, that one <hi>Minacious</hi> word was ſpoken after he got up. I need not declare the Perjuries of <hi>Lucas</hi> his Widdow, or her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Kelland,</hi> they being much the ſame at the Aſſizes, that they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Coroner, except one Addition that <hi>Kelland</hi> made, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Lucas</hi> not only from time to time complained of his Beating, but ſpit Blood, and brought up Knots of Blood as big as <hi>French Nuts</hi> at his Mouth, and that much Blood went from him by Stool. To all that hath been Evidenced by ſuch near Relations, and others to prove Rationally the contrary, I will add the Authentick Evidence of Mr. <hi>George Sutchcot</hi> (who is known to be no Friend to <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> nor their <hi>Meetings;</hi> but a moſt Intimate and Familiar Converſer with the Informers, being judg'd by many to be an <hi>Abettor,</hi> and Encourager of them) which was this. That though <hi>Lucas</hi> the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his pretended Beating, complain'd to him thereof, yet he wrought with him ſeveral Months after, without failing any thing in his Work, and he never heard him to complain more of it. I could Write much more to Confirm what hath been Aſſerted, but let this Suffice, till there be need of further Evidence.</p>
            <p>I will now proceed to the Narration of the Judges Partiality, I will not ſay Injuſtice, and apparent Malice. Firſt, It's evidenced that the Judg came Prejudiced to the Tryal of the Priſoners, and had hearkned to their Enemies Informations before he came; for at Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les</hi> Tryal at the <hi>Niſi Prius</hi> Bench, when there was an occaſion to ſpeak of the <hi>Conventicle</hi> held at Mr. <hi>H.</hi> when <hi>Lucas</hi> was diſarm'd, and of the Barbarous, and rude Carriage of the Informers; he juſtified them, and ſaid, it was well they were all Arm'd (or word to that purpoſe) or they might all have been Murdered at it as <hi>Lucas</hi> was, whom he declar'd was then Murdered, for want of Arms to defend himſelf: All which was before the Tryal of the Priſoners, whereby it evidently appears with what prejudice he was poſſeſt, and how little he intended to do Juſtice.</p>
            <p>He gave alſo the Witneſſes againſt the Priſoners, the utmoſt Liberty to declare themſelves; and when Mr. <hi>John Bear</hi> Swore ſo deſperately by Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and Information, and <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p,</hi> and <hi>Campion,</hi> did in their <hi>Oath</hi> contradict themſelves, he took no notice of it: But the Witneſſes for the Priſoners were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53767:12"/> Snib'd, and Diſcouraged not a little by him, he lying ſtill at the Catch, to make their Evidence to Interfere; he uſed likewiſe all ways to <hi>Nonplus,</hi> and daunt them, that they might not have boldneſs to declare the Truth. The <hi>Mother</hi> therefore of <hi>Lucas,</hi> when ſhe came to Evidence for the Priſoners, he aſked her, How much Money was given her for her Sons Blood? And told her, ſhe came to Sell it for Money (or words to that purpoſe) he Taunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Scornfully reflected upon Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> likewiſe, who was deſired to be a Witneſs for the Priſoners; ſaying, He thought it a fine thing to ſtand there to own a Cauſe. So he dealt with another Perſon (who was a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Witneſs in the behalf of the Priſoners) floutingly: Telling him, That he was dreſt up in a Coat, or Cloke, with a fine made Story. To another Witneſs Jeeringly, and Scoffingly, he ſaid: He did believe that ſhe was one of <hi>them,</hi> for ſhe did <hi>Tone</hi> it out like one of them. The Coroner likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſired to ſpeak ſomething of the death of <hi>Lucas,</hi> was ſuffered to ſay little or nothing, the Judg telling him, That Coroners were wont to be Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with: And when he came to give Inſtructions to the Jury, and to Sum up the Evidence, againſt, and for the Priſoners, he Omitted moſt of the material Circumſtances that made for them; and told the Jury they muſt find it <hi>Wilful Murder,</hi> or nothing. And when the <hi>Jury</hi> brought in their Verdict not Guilty, he ſeem'd to be diſcontented, not letting the Priſoners depart, without Slurring them in the open Court, and rendring them as Odious as he could: Telling them, That though Men had Acquitted them, yet there was a God that knew they were Guilty, of that they are charged with (or words to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) I ſhall leave the Impartial Reader to Judg thereof.</p>
            <p>And now that none may <hi>Ignore,</hi> or be Unacquainted with the true Ground and Reaſon of this Violent, and Virulent Proſecution of ſo many Innocent perſons: I ſhall but briefly relate a few Paſſages, <hi>viz. George Bear</hi>'s words (who Swore deſperately enoug among the reſt) who when he heard what full Evidence was given for the Priſoners, ſwelling with Indignation, burſt forth into theſe Audable words, which contain'd a Diabolical Imprecation, to this purpoſe: <hi>The Pox of God take them, they will be all Acquitted.</hi> The Widdow of <hi>Lucas</hi> returning home, did Chide her Mother in Law, for the Evidence ſhe gave, and told her if ſhe had been good (or words to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) ſhe might have got her a Thouſand Pound: The Mother replied, What Advantage could it be to you, if the Priſoners had been Hang'd? The <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> replied, Rather than ſo they would have given her a good part of their Eſtates. Juſtice <hi>Bear,</hi> when the firſt Examination of matter of Fact was, and <hi>Lucas</hi> his own Father was Summoned before him, who Swearing that they were but <hi>Strakes</hi> upon his Back, made with the folding of his Waſtcoat, and Shirt, which <hi>Kelland</hi> ſwore were the Impreſt blows; he commanded his Clerk to Write down Stripes. The Coroner that came firſt, (as I have told the Reader) went away without doing his Office: I will not abſolutely determine who was the cauſe, or what was the reaſon of it; but we have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Notorious</hi> Exidence, and <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of Fact, from Mr. <hi>Bears</hi> ſending for the Coroner, that came upon notice given him by the Accuſed, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to go. Now I leave it to the Ingenuous, and Judicious Reader, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in his own thoughts, whether this eager Proſecution was to Vindicate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53767:13"/> 
               <hi>Inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſpilt, or to ſpill <hi>Innocent Blood,</hi> Now if it be queſtioned by any, What's the reaſon Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks</hi> did not appear with the other Eight, that his Innocency aſwel as theirs, might be cleared? The Anſwer is briefly this: That he being at ſome conſiderable diſtance from his own Houſe, when Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> ſo Illegally, and Maliciouſly purſued him with a <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry,</hi> and never being where it came, he judg'd it fit, with many others, to take no Notice of it, but enioy his Liberty till the <hi>Aſſizes;</hi> when, if he were Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the <hi>Grand J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Murder found againſt him, with the Feſt, he intended to make his Appearance, and put himſelf upon his Tryal, if he could have any hopes of Juſtice, and Moderation: But underſtanding how the <hi>Judg</hi> did prejudg the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>act, calling it Murder, when the Tryal was betwixt Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and one of the Informers; and how thoſe that were <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> then againſt Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> did moſt prodigiouſly Perjure themſelves, and who were to be Witneſſes againſt himſelf; and not being Ignorant how Active, and Induſtrious ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſticks,</hi> or <hi>Hierarchiſts,</hi> were to Ruine him if they could (<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arn'd;</hi> for that end, ſome ſaying, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g for all the reſt</hi>) conſidering with all theſe things, the Care and Induſtry of the Under-Sheriff, to have a <hi>Grand Jury</hi> ſo Conſtituted, as the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rder</hi> might be found againſt him, with the Reſt. He had good reaſon to Suſpect, and Fear, that he had alſo provided ſuch a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tty J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would gratifie the Malice of his Enemies, and into whoſe hands it would not be ſafe for him to put his Life. Upon all theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages he thought it not fit to yield, and give up himſelf to thoſe who Intended, and Attempted ſo Voraciouſly to make a <hi>Prey</hi> of him. If it be ſaid — <hi>Hic ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. And that Abſconding, and Flying, argues Guilt. I Anſwer, That ſometimes the moſt Unſtained, Unſpotted <hi>Righteoſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Virgin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> cannot ſtand before malicious Fury, and powerful Malice, or devouring Envy Arm'd with power (which made the <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſay, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>metimes the Righteous d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in his Righteouſneſs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>gth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wicked, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the other, though both be</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) and when it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo, it's no diſhonour to any perſon to ſecure himſelf by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doth it Adminiſter a juſt ground of jealouſie in any other, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the caſe of Guilt, which it cannot in the leaſt Infer. What Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth, many who have been in the ſame Circumſtances, have done. But this is not all that he hath to plead for himſelfe; For there is Impriſonment, which his Enemies deſign againſt him, ſo if they cannot deprive him of his Life, they will of his Liberty; and Liberty being more Eligible, and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able than Reſtraint, he is reſolv'd to enjoy it as long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he can. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he deſirs may be Publiſhed to the whole World, that let him have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> before a Juſt, Upright, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aft Judg, and have a Jury of Indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Indicious perſons, not choſen by Malice, and Prejudice; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f he be not found Guilty, he ſhall have his Liberty, He will p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it, for the clearing of his Innocency.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to give the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fully, and Impartially of the Tryals that were betwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Baſtard,</hi> Eſquires, and Mr. <hi>Edward R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynel,</hi> and <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Bear,</hi> for pretended
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53767:13"/> Neglects of putting the <hi>Act</hi> againſt <hi>Conventicl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Execution,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt <hi>Infomer</hi> Sued Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> for three Neglects, and ſo was in hopes of having one Moity of Three Hundred Pounds, however his Majeſty would diſpoſe of the other (it's likely he was not without hopes of it, as the Merited reward of his Signal, and eminent Service) now let the World know the Ingratitude, and Diſingenuity of <hi>Edward Reynel,</hi> towards Mr. <hi>Hele,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he is his God-Son, but as he at that time Owed him ſeveral Sums of Money, both on his own, and Fathers Accounts; his Elder Brother, Mr. <hi>George Reynel</hi> (the Priſoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and the Juſtice) Owing him likewiſe an Hundred Pound, which his Lady ſent for ſome Years ſince, to pay her Phiſitians with, and had it from him, only on her ſingle Letter, without Bill, or Bond, and which is not Paid to this day, He is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to requite Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> well, for all his Civilities, and Favours ſhewed to him, and the Family. The other Informer Sued Mr. <hi>Baſtard,</hi> for two Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, and now thought to enrich himſelf with the ſhare of the Two Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound, thereby to get above the Diſgrace, and Contempt of Poverty: <hi>Non habet infaelix paupertas durius in ſe, quam quod rediculos homines facit</hi>— In this Account which I give, I ſhall as before Methodize, and Digeſt it into this Order. Firſt, To relate the Perjuries of the Witneſſes that ſware againſt both the Gentlemen, and the hard Meaſure they met with from the Judg; who ſet himſelf with that Violence, and Vehemency againſt them, that it was obſerved, and ſpoken of generally with Abhorrency, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Tryal was put forth after four days Attendance on the Aſſizes, and the Jury call'd, <hi>Robert Adams,</hi> of <hi>Malborough,</hi> being the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of it, was excepted againſt by Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice</hi> (who was not long before the Principal <hi>Informer</hi>) as an <hi>Excommunicated</hi> Perſon, for which he took his Oath in the Court, whereby the ſaid <hi>R. A.</hi> was Incapaciated to ſerve in the Tryal, relating to Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Now the Reader muſt know, that the foreſaid Perſon was ſuſpected by the Informers, to Favour, or bear <hi>Good-will</hi> towards thoſe they call <hi>Fanaticks;</hi> and they could contrive no way to remove him but this, to prove he was not Capable of ſerving as a Juror (which by the Law no Excommunicated perſon is) Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he undertakes for an Expedient, and that is, to call the Omniſcient God, and Him that is <hi>Eſſential,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Truth,</hi> to be a Witneſs to a Lye. For ſince the Aſſizes, it hath been enquired into, and found that <hi>Robert Adams</hi> was not then Excommunicated. M. <hi>Bear</hi> further Swore, to Aggravate Mr, <hi>Heles</hi> ſuppoſed Neglects, that the Inſolency of <hi>Conventiclers</hi> was grown to that height, that all Loyal Subjects had juſt cauſe to fear a Rebellion: That they (ſpeaking of Mr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> and the people he Preacht too, did not only Uſurpt the <hi>Pulpits</hi> of Lawful Miniſters, but pull'd them out of their Pulpits, and laid Church-wardens that came to Suppreſs them, flat on their Backs in the Church, and broke open Church Doors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which things, if Truths, Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> was never an Eye-witneſs of: But what Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious falſhoods theſe are, the whole Countrey round about knows. It's ſtrange, and moſt Inconſiſtent with Reaſon, that they who were continually Attempting to bring Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> into trouble for Preaching, ſhould never take
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53767:14"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o great, and fair an Advantage againſt him, as hereby they had. If Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> can produce one Church-warden, or any Officer in a Town, or Pariſh where Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Preacht publickly, that will affirm, that either he oppoſed him, or that any Aſſault, or the leaſt Violence, and Incivility was offered by him, or any of his Hearers, upon the Account of his Preaching; or can bring one Miniſter to prove that ever Mr. <hi>H.</hi> or any of his Hearers did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs him of a Pulpit, when he was in it; or that any Church Doors were Broke open to poſſeſs the Pulpits, then will I engage Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> ſhall appear at any Aſſizes, or any other time, to ſuffer whatever any Law in the utmoſt Extremity can Inflict upon him, and promiſe never to Indite Mr. <hi>B.</hi> for Perjury.</p>
            <p>The Jury being Sworn, one Witneſs upon Oath, Swore that Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take Informations upon Oath, that there was a Conventicle at Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> his Houſe, <hi>May</hi> the 19th. When another of them upon his Oath did confeſs, and acknowledg, that Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> did take their Informations, which alſo ſeveral perſons of Mr. <hi>Heles</hi> Houſe, did Atteſt. As for the other two Neglects Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> was charged with, and Sued for, which were in one day, <hi>June</hi> the 19th. 1670. I ſhall ſpeak nothing concerning them, till I relate the Carriage of the Judg, in reference to them.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Tryal</hi> betwixt Mr. <hi>Baſtard,</hi> and <hi>John Bear,</hi> was put on for two Neglects, the firſt being for the 29th. of <hi>June.</hi> Likewiſe, one of the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and the <hi>Dog-whipper,</hi> Swore they came between Twelve and One a Clock, to Mr. <hi>Baſtards</hi> houſe, to Inform of a Conventicle near <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> in Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his Houſe; and that it was three miles betwixt <hi>Gorſton</hi> (where Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> dwells) and <hi>Kingsbridg;</hi> but the contrary to all that they affirmed upon <hi>Oath,</hi> was ſo fully prov'd, that all who heard it, might, and moſt were convinced what perjur'd <hi>Miſcreants</hi> they were: <hi>Campion</hi> Swore that he ſaw Miſtriſs <hi>Baſtard, Mr. Baſtards</hi> Wife, at the ſame Conventicle, whereas it can be prov'd ſhe was elſewhere, by ſeveral Witneſſes. Should I publiſh to the World all the falſe <hi>Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Voluminous</hi> perjuries of theſe, and other Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the Narrative would break the bounds, and ſtretch it ſelf far beyond the Conſines, I intend it ſhall be kept within. I ſhall now conclude all with the Carriage of the Judg, who ſuffered without any <hi>Check, Mr. Hele,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Baſtard,</hi> to be Jeared and Flouted, and high Affronts put upon them, by ſuch <hi>Humuncios,</hi> and <hi>Dregs</hi> of <hi>Humanity,</hi> as <hi>Campion,</hi> the <hi>Smith, Leech</hi> (the <hi>Judas</hi>) that's glad of a days work in the Countrey, the <hi>Dog Whipper,</hi> and others. When <hi>Campion</hi> ſwore he ſaw <hi>Mr. Baſtards</hi> Wife at a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and the Judg aſked him, How he knew it was her? He moſt Saucily, and Impudently replied: He could not tell whether ſhe was Married to him, or no, but he had had ſeveral Children by her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet the Judg did not in the leaſt reprove him for, or ſhew the leaſt diſlike of his ſo ſhamefully abuſing Perſons of that <hi>Worth,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> they are known, and eſteemed generally to be. When <hi>Leech</hi> ſware, That if <hi>Mr. Baſtard</hi> had been ſo zealous in Executing the Kings Laws, as he was to maintain <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticlers had been all Routed before that time; the Judg did not in the leaſt Check him, for that high and moſt ſcandalous Charge, but ſeemed rather to be delighted with it, and all the reſt of that filthy <hi>Traſh.</hi> He ſuffered
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53767:14"/> likewiſe the very Council to be Flouted by ſome of the <hi>Varlots,</hi> as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Campion,</hi> whom he permitted as long as he pleaſed, to Act the parts of a <hi>Fool</hi> in the <hi>Play,</hi> to make <hi>Sport</hi> for, and move Laughter in Court; and he himſelf Reflected ſufficiently upon the Gentlemen, inſomuch that one of them told him, if he were an offence to him, he would go out of the Court. Yea, he Laboured to Diſcourage their Councel, and to prevent their full, and effectual Pleading for their Clients: Telling them, he was ſorry to ſee any Plead in ſuch a Cauſe, bidding them for ſhame to hold their peace (or to that purpoſe) but ſaid, he thought what they did, was for their Fees. When the Councel for the Informers, had all deſirable Liberty to ſpeak, yea, and were often eaſed, and Aſſiſted by him. And though as to the firſt Neglect, <hi>Mr. Hele</hi> was Sued for, it was fully proved, that he did not refuſe to take the Informations of the Witneſſes, by the acknowledgment of ſome of them in the Court, aſwel as by the Evidence of his own Servants; and none could Swear that there was either Praying, or Preaching, or any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip diſſonant from the Liturgy, and Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> at that time, but that about three Fields off (beſides a high Houſe, that the Voice was to aſcend over) they heard a Voice, which they conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, came from <hi>Mr. H.</hi> his Houſe: Yet he gave a ſtrict charge to the Jury, to find for the Informers, the Plantiffs. Concerning the two other Neglects, which were for one day, the one for the Forenoon, the other for the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, how the Judg ſuffered Juſtice to take Place, and Sway; what follows may give the Reader ample Satisfaction. In reference to the Forenoons Neglect, the Witneſſes Sware that they were at <hi>Pool (Mr. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les</hi> Pariſh Church) about Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon, to Acquaint him with a Conventicle at <hi>Mr. H.</hi> his Houſe, which was confeſt upon Oath by them, ended a conſiderable time before <hi>Mr. Hele</hi> had any Notice of it; and yet it was judg'd a Neglect, that <hi>Mr. Hele</hi> came not ſoon enough to Suppreſs the ſame: And as to the other pretended Neglect in the Afternoon, though <hi>Mr. Hele</hi> prov'd, he ſent immediately for his Horſes to be fitted for him againſt he came from Church; and after he had refreſht himſelf with ſome meat, he came to <hi>Mr. Hicks</hi> his Houſe, where he found neither Preaching nor Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither could any of the Informers Swear there was any; but they heard a Voice of one in ſuch an Exerciſe, and that it was <hi>Mr. Hicks</hi>'s Voice (which was deſperate enough, ſeeing Voices are many times as like as Faces) and that this <hi>Conventicle</hi> began at a Eleven a Clock, and ended at Two (which was more than <hi>Mr. Hele</hi> then knew) yet not the leaſt Grane of Allowance, muſt be laid in the Ballance for <hi>Mr. Hele;</hi> and whatever was ſaid by his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, was ſufficient to Preponderate, whatever might rationally be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to Acquit him from the Guilt of a Witting, and wilful Neglect of his Duty (the moſt Rigid, and Severe Interpretation, being put upon all his Actions, and the ſmalleſt Circumſtance aggravated to the higheſt Pitch, that it was poſſible for Malice, and Prejudice to Rack, and Screw it up to) as that it's Contravertible, and Diſputable, whether the Act doth require a Juſtice of Peace to come in Perſon to any place, where he is Inform'd a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle is, there's no ſuch Law expreſt; if there be any thing of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it's but very Darkly imply'd. And further, that he was Engaged in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53767:15"/> the Publick <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God when the Informers came: And ſhould he leave that, to Ride Three or Four mile upon an uncertainty at the beſt? (And if he had come, it had been to no purpoſe, there being no Meeting at that time) And after the Worſhip was over, it was moſt reaſonable that Nature ſhould be refreſht, before he Ride ſo far? And yet he came at the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable time to find a Conventicle, which was about Two a Clock, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and uſual time, that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> was wont with the People, to meet at his Houſe. And certainly, if the Informers had not Alarum'd them by their coming, before the Juſtice, he had Surprized, and found them all like <hi>Bees</hi> in the <hi>Hive</hi> together; And when he came, none did Swear that there had been any Worſhip of God, only a Voice of one Praying, or Preaching, was heard, and it was Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi>'s. And ſuppoſe it had been ſo, they did not Swear that it was to above the Number of Five: It's true, Mr. <hi>Hele</hi> found ſome Women in the Houſe, and he Aſkt them, How they came there? And how, or when, or to what end they came: How could he know? Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> had a Child very Sick, and they were with his <hi>Wife,</hi> in the Chamber where the Child lay: And how this could be a <hi>Notorious Evidence,</hi> and Circumſtance of Fact (that is ſuch a Circumſtance, that carries in it, a certain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fact, coming within the compaſs of that <hi>Axiome,</hi> or, <hi>Maxim poſitâ Circumſtantia rei, ponitur res ipſa:</hi> For it's Abſurd otherwiſe to Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Law the two former ways of Conviction, <hi>viz.</hi> Confeſſion of the Party: Or the Oath of two Witneſſes, being certain <hi>Quoad Nos,</hi> the laſt muſt be of the ſame kind) to him, that there had been Religious Worſhip, and differing from the Liturgy, and Practice of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> or a ſufficent Reaſon to prove him Guilty of a <hi>Witting,</hi> or Wilful Neglect of Duty, let all Sober, Impartial, or Unprejudiced men judg. However, the Judg ſtrictly chargeth the Jury (which deſtroys the Liberty of a Judgment of Diſcretion, aſwel as of Determination in them, and ſo makes <hi>Juries</hi> to ſignifie nothing) to find three Neglects, which is more than the Law (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that are Judicious rationally ſuppoſe) doth charge him with, or any other man; for it doth not ſay <hi>Toties Quoties,</hi> or ſo often as a Juſtice doth not Convict of a Conventicle when he may, he ſhall Forfeit ſo many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds, but not doing his Duty he ſhall Forfeit one Hundred Pound; When our <hi>Wiſe</hi> Legiſlators intended, that Conventiclers ſhould ſuffer for every particular Crime, they Expreſs it: Why then ſhould we think, much leſs abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely determine, that ſeeing they have not expreſt it with reſpect to Juſtices of the Peace, that they did certainly intend it. The <hi>Jury</hi> having this charge given them, after ſome time, bring in their <hi>Verdict</hi> to the Judges Chamber, of Two Hundred Pounds for two Neglects only; at which, he was highly diſpleaſed, and would not receive their <hi>Verdict,</hi> till they brought it in for Three.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> producing ſuch full proof, and clear Evidence to Acquit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from one Neglect he was charged with, and Sued for, he was reſolved to make him Guilty of the other; therefore, though Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> prov'd that he took all the Informations of the Informers, and every word that they ſaid in reference to the ſame, and every Name of the Perſons, that they affirmed were then preſent: To which Informations likewiſe, the ſeveral
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53767:15"/> Informers put their hands, but without any proof, that there was either Preaching or Praying (Mr. <hi>John Bear</hi> upon his Oath, acknowledging he ſaw, or knew of no manner of Worſhip among the people; and the reſt, that there was no Worſhip contrary to the Liturgy, and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>) And notwithſtanding this, though Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> (that he might not Neglect his Duty) made a Record hereof as a Conventicle, which was put in at the next Seſſions; and the Money return'd of thoſe Offenders (whom two of the Informers ſware, were there preſent) ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd the King; yet the Judg declared it a Neglect, becauſe the Record was not Dated the Firſt day of the Seſſions, but the Third. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Baſtard</hi> declared openly, and in the Face of the Court, that he did not Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his Duty <hi>Wittingly,</hi> and <hi>Wilfully</hi> (which are the expreſs Words of the Act againſt Conventicles) for he could aſwel have Dated it the Firſt, as the Third day; but he knew nothing to the contrary, but that it was Valid enough if Entred, and Dated any time during the Seſſions (which are taken in a general Senſe, every particular day not being a <hi>New,</hi> or diſtinct Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) and what Unprejudiced Perſons can rationally think, or judg other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: However, according to the Directions given to the Jury, he was Fined a Hundred Pound. Now if the Reader be curiouſly Inquiſitive to know what <hi>Judg</hi> this was, that ſo far Deviated, and Swerv'd from all Juſtice, and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, leaſt any other ſhould be cenſured for him, I muſt declare; it was Judg <hi>Rainford,</hi> who is profoundly Wiſe, and Underſtanding in the Law, Mild, Compaſſionate, and Impartial in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, here in <hi>England</hi> (for ought I ever heard to the contrary) except when the Cauſes of thoſe call'd <hi>Fanaticks</hi> come before him; and then like <hi>Naaman,</hi> he muſt be pardoned.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Aſhbrenton,</hi> near <hi>Totneſs,</hi> on, or about <hi>June</hi> the 12th. one <hi>Andrew Helly,</hi> with his Son, Daughter, and a Friend, were Repeating a Sermon in a Barn of his, about a mile from his Houſe; to which place, juſt as they had ended, came <hi>James Parrat,</hi> and a private Perſon, the <hi>Setting-Dogs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abroad, Scented, and eſpied the Game, and rather than they would not be rewarded for their pains, reſolutely Sware, he was the Miniſter; and ſo the Number Five is made up, and conſequently a Meeting prov'd, and Preaching too Logically concluded. So <hi>Parrat,</hi> that was never near the place till all was done, was Fined Twelve Pound, <hi>A. H.</hi> and his Relations, Twenty Eight Pound; and this was done by Juſtice <hi>Fowel,</hi> and J. <hi>Kelland,</hi> who made the Evidence of Informers (that are parties) the ground of this Conviction, which was againſt all Reaſon, and Law. For ſuppoſe the Barn part of the Dwelling-houſe (which is about a mile diſtant from it) then though <hi>J. P.</hi> had been preſent, and a Preacher too, there could be no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, <hi>A. H.</hi> and his Children being of the Family: Let it be taken other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, yet <hi>Parat</hi> not being there, there could be no <hi>Conventicle,</hi> the other not being a Number above what the Law allows; ſo the place was not liable to Twenty pounds. But grant that he were there, yet not being a Miniſter, or if he were, yet he neither Preaching, nor Teaching, no Law doth puniſh for Twenty pounds more. But the Juſtices were reſolved to ſet this <hi>Poor Barn,</hi> like a Shepherds Tent, on Wheels, carrying it home to the precincts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53767:16"/> of the Dwelling-houſe, for the Fining of that, and then Recarrying it to the Fields, for the Fining of the people. The Agrieved become Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents to the Seſſions, where they find no Relief, or Redreſs, but great Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; inſtead of a <hi>Plaiſter,</hi> their Heads are Broken more, they are Caſt, and Treble Coſts they muſt pay for their <hi>Traverſe,</hi> which is always an <hi>Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole</hi> in the Exceſs, never in the Defect, at the Seſſions.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Silverton,</hi> near <hi>Exon,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Sainthil,</hi> Seiſed ſome perſons, with a Non-conformiſt, Mr. <hi>Treg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs</hi> (I hope now after all his Storms, Arrived at the Haven of his everlaſting Reſt) in a private Houſe, about Nine a Clock in the morning, and Fined the Houſe Twenty pound; and though he could not prove that there was any Preaching, or Teaching (as there was none) yet ſome of the people were Fined for the Miniſter, Twenty pound more: Though he had an Eſtate of his own, which he Acquainted the <hi>Juſtice</hi> with, and deſired he might bear his own Fine, but the Gentleman would not grant it: The Agrieved appeal to the General Seſſions, where they Traverſe with ſome good Succeſs, touching the Preachers Fine, his Conviction not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Recorded; which the Appellants Advocate obſerved to Advantage: But yet the Remedy was almoſt as bad, if not worſe than the Diſeaſe; for being found Guilty of the <hi>Meeting,</hi> though not of Preaching; they were Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Judg of the Seſſions, Mr. <hi>Carew,</hi> to pay treble Coſts as high, as if they had been Caſt in both parts.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Exon,</hi> there lives an Old Gentleman, called Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> a Juſtice of Peace in the City, who hath been a Notorious Conventicle-Hunter many years, the Fame whereof is diffuſed through all the <hi>Weſt:</hi> The <hi>Ardours</hi> of whoſe <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi> when he is to Engage in this Honourable Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo far Tranſports him, that many times he becomes a compleat <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedlamus;</hi> his <hi>Geſtures, Poſtures, Ravings,</hi> much reſemble theirs, whom I have ſeen bound in Chains, which the Boys in the City can Act, and Imitate with admirable Dex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, though no doubt he deſerves for them a <hi>Canoniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Saint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hip,</hi> but by the <hi>Romiſh Church;</hi> becauſe he's never zealous for the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> and an eſteem of a greater Wit, becauſe what he hath, appears hereby to be mixt with <hi>Madneſs.</hi> I might Write Voluminouſly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but I will Omit, and paſs by all things concerning him, except this one, which the Reader may be pleaſed to caſt his Eye upon, thereby to take a meaſure, and judg of all the reſt. One Evening upon Information given him by ſome of his <hi>Familia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> that there was a <hi>Meeting</hi> of the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> at Mr. <hi>A. Jeffreys,</hi> thether he haſtens as the Eagle to the prey; when he came to the Houſe, the Doors without delay were opened to him, there he finds about ſixteen perſons, moſt of them Relations of the Family, and Invited to <hi>Supper;</hi> but this Quick-ſcented Juſtice ſmells another Feaſt in his Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticling-Fancy, and judging rather by Number of the perſons, than weight of Reaſon, after ſome wonted Ravings, and Ragings, Fines the Houſe Twenty pound for a Suppoſed <hi>Meeting;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chriſpin,</hi> beſides his own Mulct and his Wifes, was Fined for ſeveral Rich perſons, directly contrary to Law, which makes the <hi>Rich</hi> to pay for the <hi>Poor</hi> only (not whom a Juſtice ſhall judg to be ſo, but who are really to be ſo.) Mr. <hi>J.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> appeal from the Rage of one ſingle Juſtice, to the Reaſon of a <hi>Bench:</hi> At the City Seſſions they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53767:16"/> Traverſe their Appeal, where Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> was not only Judg, but Witneſs in his own Caſe; his Oath moſt unreaſonably taken, and as falſly he Swears in the Face of the Court. That when he came to Mr. <hi>Jeffreys</hi> Houſe, he could have no entrance, but was forced Violently to break open the Door, inſomuch that he made the Staple flye; the contrary whereunto was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prov'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Maſter of the Houſe opened the Door quietly, and ſeaſonably; the Attendants that ſtood by, perceiv'd no ſuch effects of his Vigour, and Vivacity. But no wonder to hear a falſe Oath drop from a falſe Lip, that hath cauſed a Wide-mouth'd untruth, to paſs proverbially under the Name of a <hi>Butler:</hi> But happily he might Lodg ſome mental reſerve, for a Salvo to his Oath, and ſo be able to ſay with that prophane, and profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated Wretch— <hi>Jur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, at mentem injuratam Gero.</hi> It was likewiſe Sworn, if I miſtake not, by ſome of his Setting-Dogs, that the Meat was laid down to the Fire, after, or about the time they entered the Houſe; which was prov'd by the Appellants, to be then near half Roaſted, and that all the <hi>Harbingers</hi> of a Supper, were there. But however, though they did ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently Invalidate all Circumſtances of Fact, that the Juſtice would ground his Conviction of a Conventicle upon, yet it was to no purpoſe: For Juſtice <hi>Carew</hi> ſitting as Deputy Recorder, and Judg of the Seſſions, ſo inſtructed the Jury-men, who were fit to receive his Impreſſions, that they brought in their <hi>Verdict</hi> againſt the Appellants, and they are Laden with treble Coſts, according to the liberal Calculation of the Judg.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Derwood,</hi> near <hi>Exon,</hi> on a Lords-Day, a little after the 10th of <hi>May,</hi> ſome perſons met together in a Wood, but not ſo cloſe as to eſcape the Eagle eyes of the Informers, who obſerv'd their going in, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded confidently to be a <hi>Conventicle.</hi> The adjacent Pariſh <hi>upton-pines,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeedily Alarum'd herewith, from thence ruſh forth with all Expedition, and Fury, a company of Club-men, whereof the Son of the Pariſh Prieſt was one, and fall violently upon one perſon; which madneſs, when a Sober, Honeſt man rebuked, telling them he would go without compulſion; they outragiouſly fell upon him, Drawing, and Dragging him along, ſome taking hold of his Arms, ſome of his Legs, and ſo rudely was he handled, that he Recovered not for ſome conſiderable time of thoſe Diſtortions, Compreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Contuſions, which his Body ſuffered by them. At laſt, ſome few of them (the reſt eſcaping) were brought before Juſtice <hi>Tackfield</hi> (that <hi>bluſtering Tempeſt</hi> of <hi>Wrath,</hi> and <hi>Rage,</hi> againſt his <hi>Fanatical</hi> Neighbours) where being in an outward Room, they heard what the Informers Sware be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>viz.</hi> That they heard a Voice, but whether there was either Prayer, or Preaching, they could not tell. However, this <hi>Don Farioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (that he might make ſome further Compenſation for his Notorious <hi>Quandam Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm</hi>) Convicts of a Conventicle, Fines ſome of the people for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſome for a Miniſter, though none could be ſo much as prov'd to be there, much leſs to Preach, or Teach: But, <hi>Corruptio optima eſt poſſima,</hi> Which is not only true Phyſically, but Morally.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Darlington</hi> near <hi>Totneſs,</hi> Goodman <hi>Searls</hi> Houſe was Viſited upon ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of a <hi>Meeting;</hi> by Mr. <hi>Tho. Carew,</hi> where he found but one Perſon (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Family) <hi>Viz.</hi> a Kindſman of the ſaid <hi>Searls.</hi> But the quick-ſighted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53767:17"/> Juſtice in a certain Room finds many Spittle spots, and thence by Logical Deduction Concludes it a <hi>Company,</hi> and at next ſtep a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> Two or three being met in a certain Field, at ſome diſtance from the Houſe: now a moſt dim ſuſpicion is made, a very demonſtrative cercumſtance, and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious evedence that God had been worſhipped there by more then Four, beſides the Family, or that there was a <hi>Meeting</hi> for ſuch an end. When a man looks through a multiplying, and magnifying Glaſs of malice, the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uteſt circumſtance ſhall be ſubſtance enough, and a dark ſhadow a clear Sun-beam: rather therefore then he will not attain his end, even that which is next to nothing ſhall be a ſufficient ground to paſs a Conviction upon; So now wo be to the Rheumatck People, for they muſt pay large Fees when this Man is their Phyſitian, twenty pownd therefore muſt the ſhoulders of the poor man (the Maſter of the Family) bear the weight off; and unleſs he and his Family will forbear ſpitting, when together, he may be in danger of paying more: but all that this Juſtice doth, is little enough to Compur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and abſolve himſelf from the Imputation of <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> and he muſt be pardoned if he ſhew his Valour in this Cauſe, as he once did in another of a differant Character, when a Champion in Captain <hi>Braddons</hi> Troope,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven.</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> being ſo nearly Conjoyn'd, and ſuch frindly Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, it may not be impertinent, and unlawful to caſt an Occular glance upon the Borders, and Fronteirs of it; where there is a Tovvn call'd <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drake,</hi> vulgarly <hi>Larrake,</hi> at which lives an Aged Reverend Divine, whoſe vvorth is furrher knovvn then his ovvn Country, a Non-conformiſt, by name <hi>Mr. Gaſper Hicks,</hi> Who continuing to Preach in his Family ſince the 10. of <hi>May,</hi> 1670. to the Number that the <hi>Act</hi> againſt Conventicles allovvs of, vvith others under 16 years of age, it did highly inrage a young <hi>Levite</hi> of Jejune, and Immature Braines; Who Serves for the Pariſh Prieſt, by Name Mr. <hi>Winnel,</hi> or <hi>Windle;</hi> this Supercelious, Pragmatical, and ſelf-conceited Novice reſolves therefore to injure as much as poſibly he could, him vvhom he ought to have rever'd and had in high Veneration; to accompliſh his end he ſticks not to turn Informer (the moſt diſhonorable and imfamous <hi>Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> upon the Earth) againſt him, that he kept Conventicles, he gets the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Pariſh to ſearch his houſe, vvho found none but four Perſons of or above the age of 16, vvith ſome fevv under, beſides his ovvn Family: Hovvever this <hi>Munſeur Furibundo,</hi> rides from Juſtice to Juſtice to make a conviction; but theſe worthy and noble Gentlemen that were his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who have right reſentments of Genoroſity, and walke according to the Rules of Juſtice and Equity, as Sir <hi>J. C.</hi> Sir <hi>W. M.</hi> Mr. <hi>S.</hi> would give him no Countenance, knowing the Law was not violated by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Then he ſpurs up his Horſe further Weſtward, where he met with ſome Juſtices, who like Tinder preſently took fire; upon the firſt Information: (I know not all their Names, but one of them was Dr. <hi>Polewheel,</hi> that terrible <hi>Fulminoſo,</hi> who for theſe 10 or 11 years paſt, hath anhelated nothing but threatning cruelty againſt thoſe Catachreſtically called <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aticks</hi>) with the higheſt impetuoſity and rage; Theſe Juſtices fall upon <hi>Mr. H.</hi> creating ſomething out of nothing, they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict him of a <hi>Converticle</hi> kept in his own houſe, and likewiſe take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, without any proof, that he Preached, and ſo Levy 40<hi>l.</hi> upon him: He
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53767:17"/> finding himſelf agrieved becomes an Appellant to the next General Seſſions, which is out of the Frying-pan into the Fire, for all Juſtice was baniſh'd from the <hi>Bench, Mr. H.</hi> was denyed a Jury, directly contrary to the Law, <hi>Page</hi> 9 <hi>of the Acts againſt Conventicles; Mr. P.</hi> and others cry'd to the Vote, which was done; and ſo not withſtanding all the ſtrenuous, and nervous endeavours of ſeveral Juſtices there to make <hi>Mr. H.</hi> his innocency a fence a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtorms and flames of the others fury, and to ſhelter him from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Judgment by an illegal Vote only paſſeth aganſt him; and his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal hereby being made unjuſt, beſides the 40<hi>l.</hi> they give treble coſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and moſt ignobly load him with ſouleſt revilings, and reproaches: never was there more monſtrous and barbarous Injuſtice acted. Firſt, that they ſhould deny the Appellant that previledge which the Law gives, and which is every <hi>Engliſh-mans</hi> Birth-right, <hi>Viz.</hi> his Tryal by a Jury. Secondly, that they ſhould judge him guilty of a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> when there were no more then four Perſons of or above the age of 16 years beſides his Family, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he accuſed of having more; but however it holds to be a <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> by a nevv nice, and ſubtle diſtinction, (which like an <hi>Ariadnes</hi> fine ſpun thread, helps and conducts them out of the Labyrinth they vvere in) <hi>viz.</hi> That though perſons under Sixteen years of Age, be no Conventiclers, yet being found with thoſe that are of, or above the ſame Age, conſtitute a Conventicle: Whereas the old Axiom is, <hi>Quicquid effecit tale, eſt magis tale.</hi> Theſe New Phyloſophers can make <hi>Non-entities,</hi> productive of <hi>Realities.</hi> Children muſt make men guilty, and yet themſelves remain Innocents ſtill. A Thouſand under the Age of Sixteen years, are Nullities in Law, but in the Execution thereof, make others Criminals and Penals too. Theſe New <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of Law make the former Criminals, but not expoſed to Penalties (though they expoſe others) and ſo makes the Law in this reſpect an ineffectual Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſuppoſing it to make Offenders, without a Sanction, and Allotment of puniſhment for them. Theſe New <hi>Arithmeticians,</hi> can make Ciphers, caſt Figures, Four above the Family in Law, is nothing, Ten Thouſand under Sixteen years, are nothing; but now according to their Rule, add nothing to nothing, and you make Five, or more. But their definitive Sentence, and final Determination by <hi>Vote</hi> (to which he muſt ſtand) ſhall make all ſound Phyloſophy, good Law, and true Arithmetick. Thirdly, That they ſhould Convict him of, and puniſh him for Preaching, when none could prove it (ſuppoſing him guilty of keeping a Conventicle) neither was there the leaſt Circumſtance to be Demonſtrative of it. It's true, our Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators have made <hi>Notorious Evidence,</hi> and Circuſtance of Fact, to prove a Conventicle, but no ſuch thing to prove Preaching, or Teaching, for it can ſcarce poſſibly admit of any proof thereby. For, grant a Miniſter be found among a people above the number of Five; What notorious Evidence can reſult from this, that he Preacht? for it might onely be (as often it is) to Pray, or his Preaching might be prevented; or grant he were ſound with his Bible, and Notes in it; yet this cannot evince clearly he did Preach: It may indeed beget a ſuſpition, that either he did, or intended to do it. But is it Legal, or Rational, to puniſh perſons upon ſo ſlender a ground as this? To inflict the Law upon him from a jealouſie of his Intentions, is to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53767:18"/> make ſuch an Act of his, or another Non-conformiſt, worſe than Murder, or Theft, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For no man is puniſht as a Felon for intending, though it be manifeſted by Attempting Felony, when it's not Actually committed. And to puniſh him for having done it, when it did not ſo appear, is equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and unreaſonable: For, <hi>De non apparentibus &amp; non-exiſtentibus eadem eſt ratio,</hi> Doth our Law condemn any Felon from a naked abſtracted Jealouſie, that he's guilty of the Crime he ſtands charged with, when there's no Evidence to prove the ſame: Our Law therefore is moſt Juſt, that Jurors muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Secundum allegata,</hi> and <hi>Probata.</hi> And that every Conviction of Guilt, and judicial Sentence muſt be Founded, and Bottom'd upon the ſame: But here was no ſuch thing to be the <hi>Baſis</hi> of the Determination at this Seſſions, by the Major part of the Bench, againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> they were therefore ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly Fluctuating, and Dubious, whether he Preacht, yea, or no, for want of clear demonſtrative Evidence: That in the Record of the Offence, it was expreſt Disjunctively that <hi>Mr. H.</hi> did Preach, or Pray, and not Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively that he did both, or poſſitively, and abſolutely he did the firſt. His Council pleaded to this, and opened the Law fully to them, ſhewing them their Groſs miſtake. But all was to them like beating the Air, for neither Law, nor the ſtrongeſt Reaſon, can be an impregnable Bulwark againſt their Envenom'd and Virulent malice, which was ſo Oppreſſingly diſgorg'd upon <hi>Mr. H.</hi> Thus Reader, thou ſeeſt how Illegally, not only in <hi>Devon,</hi> but <hi>Cornwal,</hi> many Juſtices Act, and that the New Chancery, or court of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, which ſhould be a cheriſhing Boſome to the Oppreſſed, is made a Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous, and Preſſing-ſtone for ſuch as will not yield to the unjuſt Convictions of one or more private Juſtices. Thus poor Diſtreſſed, Agrieved Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers, like unweary Birds, flie from the Hawk, into the Fowlers hand: So that henceforth, the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> muſt be the Appellants beſt Councellor, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Head broken, and being by a Friend adviſed to go to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and get the violent Fellow puniſhed: Nay, ſaid he, it's better to go to the <hi>Surgeon,</hi> to get my Head healed. The beſt Remedy for Sufferers, is to cry to that God who hath his <hi>Throne</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us) eſtabliſhed in <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> for the <hi>Habitation</hi> thereof, that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes <hi>Judgment</hi> for the Oppreſſed; that for the crying of the <hi>Poor,</hi> and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Needy,</hi> will ariſe, and from whom their cries, by reaſon of their Oppreſſions, cannot be debar'd. That will bring forth their <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> as the Light, and their <hi>Judgment</hi> as the Noon-day; who ordaineth his <hi>Arrows</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſecutors</hi> of his people. To that Eſſentially, and Eternally Juſt, and Righteous God, be Glory for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:53767:18"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THough I have given an Account to the World of thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and deplorable Oppreſſions that very many in <hi>Devon,</hi> Labour and Groan under; yet have I not made known all, for want of a perfect and true Relation thereof, neither have I decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all the unjuſtifiable Actions of their Oppreſſors: As how Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eech</hi> (the <hi>Judas</hi>) after he had Rob'd a Woman in the way as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> going home, coming towards her with his Sword drawn, demanded if her Money, which ſhe durſt not deny him. How he hath detained the Third part of the Money, due to the Poor of ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſhes, where he hath made ſeveral Conviction of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (and if I miſtake not too, after it hath been demanded) how he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uraged a Conſtable, when he was to Execute his Warrant for Diſtreſs; to take a <hi>100</hi> pounds worth of Goods, for <hi>5</hi> or <hi>6</hi> pound, telling him that he paying the Money for which the Diſtreſs was taken, he might keep the Overplus; and ſhould not be liable to return it. How he ſent a young man of <hi>Kingsbridg,</hi> to the common Goal (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law) for not coming to the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> when there was none publickly Read in the Town Church. How he bound over to two Seſſions, a perſon whom he ſuppoſed was at a <hi>Conventicle</hi> (put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to great charges and trouble) becauſe he would not take his Oath there was one, that he with <hi>Leech,</hi> might make two Witneſſes to prove the ſame. How he made the Rich pay for the rich, when he knew not how to come by their Eſtates, which is contrary to the Law; which ſaith, they muſt be poor, and unable to pay, when their Fines are to be Levied upon thoſe that are able. How he Fin'd one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that died <hi>3</hi> or <hi>4</hi> years agoe. How he commanded violently to Break open Doors to take Diſtreſs, which is not required by the Law, with many other Illegal Actions, that he's deeply guilty of. I have Omitted likewiſe the horrid Injuſtice of Sir <hi>Peter Prideux,</hi> in his dealings with Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> of <hi>Mary Otery,</hi> a Non-conformiſt.
<pb facs="tcp:53767:19"/> I have made as ſevere a Scrutiny, and Critical a Search as I poſſibly could, into the Actions of all theſe fore mentioned Juſtices, ſo far as they do reſpect the Execution of the Act againſt <hi>Conventicles;</hi> and moſt of them appears <hi>Extra,</hi> or <hi>Contra-Legal.</hi> Let but ſome of the words of the Act be examin'd and rationally weighed, in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of an unprejudiced Mind, and Judgment, and then the Illega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Proceedings, and Convictions will appear. The Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perſons prohibited to Meet is Five, of, or above <hi>16</hi> years of Age; the Ground of this Prohibition, is their Congregating or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling themſelves together <hi>under Colour,</hi> or pretence of any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Religion</hi> in other manner, than according to the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England, &amp;c. Page</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, two things muſt be proved. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there is ſome Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Religion among them. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it's diſſonant, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable both from the Liturgy, and Practice of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Which words are Copulative, and not disjunstive, ſo that if they be guilty of the one abſtracted from the other, they cannot be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the penalty of the Law: Which things were ſcarſe ever prov'd, but only taken for granted, neither is it facil, or poſſible to prove it, unleſs ſome ſhould be Eye, or Ear-witneſſes from the beginning to the end of the Meeting. If two Witneſſes ſhould come to a Conventicle, when a Non-conformiſt is Praying or Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they muſt Swear there was no Divine Exerciſe conſonant to the Liturgy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before they came; or they'l prove nothing to warrant a Legal, and rational Conviction, and if there be ſinging of Pſalms (ſuch as are allowed by Authority, and uſed publickly) Preaching, and Praying before Sermon, it's according to the practice of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> without a Worſhip agreeable to the Liturgy; yet are they not Obnoxious to puniſhment, becauſe they are not guilty of the Neglect of both, the words being as was ſaid before, <hi>Copulative,</hi> and not <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive.</hi> The Law againſt Conventicles, determines a three-fold way for proof to a Magiſtrate, to proceed unto a Conviction upon, either confeſſion of the <hi>Party;</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> of two <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> or by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>Evidence,</hi> and Circumſtance of <hi>Fact. Page 4.</hi> The two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, theſe Juſtices never had, for Informers cannot be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, being parties concern'd (to aſſert this, is as abſurd as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm a man may be a witneſ, for himſelf, or in his own cauſe) the laſt they ſeldom or never had; that is ſuch a Notirious Evidence and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
<pb facs="tcp:53767:19"/> of Fact, as is as clear and valid a proof, as the two former, for ſuch muſt it be, it is not what men judg to be ſuch from Malice, or Avarice, but what is ſo in it ſelf, for what is only productive of meer Probabilities, or Haeſitating conjectures is no proof. If a Law were made, that whoſoever goes into a <hi>Bawdy-Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Stews,</hi> to commit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs (that Reigning, predominate Beſtial ſin among us) ſhall be liable to ſuch a puniſhment, upon proof made any of theſe three ways. I believe there are ſome, very eager and zealous to Execute the Law againſt <hi>Conventicles,</hi> that would think it a very irrational and unjuſt thing to Convict a perſon of this Crime, either by his going into ſuch a place, though he was not ſeen come out, or by being ſeen to come out, though not to go in, or both, or only by being found there without any Immodeſt poſture: This is the very Caſe as to that notorious Evidence, and Circumſtance of Fact, that moſt of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices make the proof of a Conventicle. Sometimes ſeveral Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may meet together, without any ſet and ſolemn Exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and though they might intend it, yet many times it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; but going in, or coming out of a Houſe, or being found there, is made a Circumſtance evincing enough with our Juſtices. If it be Objected by way of defence, that this <hi>Act</hi> and all Clauſes therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall be conſtrued moſt Largely, and beneficially for the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing</hi> of <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and for the Jaſtification and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all perſons to be imployed in the Execution thereof, as <hi>page 12.</hi> of the Act. It may be Anſwered, That this muſt be underſtood either ſo far as things are, or perſons Act agreeable to the Rules of Common Juſtice, or Right Reaſon (though all things of that Nature be not Expreſſed in the <hi>Act</hi>) or elſe we muſt ſuppoſe his Majeſty, and our Legiſlators did intend and deſign nothing hereby but Wrong, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, which is not to be aſſerted,</p>
            <p>I hope all theſe things in Conjunction together ſeriouſly weighed, and conſidered, may rationally plead for his Majeſties interpoſing betwixt his Diſtreſſed, and Oppreſſed Subjects, and the Violence and Injuſtice of their Oppreſſers. If their Purſes (who are ſo many, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a wealthy party in this Nation) be thus Evacuted, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and ſuch a conſtant Devoration and Conſumption, made of their Eſtates by thoſe country Caterpillers (which brings not the leaſt profit of Advantage to his Majeſty, nor affords any Support to his Government,) How is it poſſible that he ſhould have adaequate and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable
<pb facs="tcp:53767:20"/> Supplies of Money to his wants? Can men make Brick without Straw? Give Money when they have it not? Or what En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement can Thouſands have (whom this <hi>Act</hi> concerns) to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove to the utmoſt, their Eſtates by Trading, when they know to what Gredy Hounds they ſhall be made a Prey. That they who are, or may (by the bleſſing of God upon their lawful Endeavours) be Rich, ſhall be reduced to miſerable Poverty, to enrich others who are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly poor, and who will not continue long Rich. I think it's not difficult to demonſtrate how the violent Execution of the <hi>Act</hi> againſt <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> hath more Enervated, and decayed Trade (which will ever prove the ſtrongeſt, and firmeſt Pillar for Government to be ſupported with, and to project, or aſſert the contrary, will terminate Indefeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably at last in a political Soleciſm) hath pauparized and Impoveriſhed more perſons, and Families in this Nation, than any one thing (yea more than many things that may be judged Burdenſome and Exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting) for theſe many years. How loud a Cry ſhould this have in the Ears of his Majeſty for ſome Indulgence, and a Relaxation of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Execution of ſuch a Law againſt ſo many Thouſands of his faithful Subjects, and to blunt the Edg of this Sword that Cuts in pieces, and mangles ſo many Members of that Body, that he is the <hi>Royal,</hi> and <hi>Supream</hi> Head of; which with much Facility may be done, not only by Vacating and Repealing the Law, or ſuperceding it by his own Prerogative, but as he hath all Executive power of Law, to hinder the Execution of it in a way Subſervient to the Malice, penury, and Avarice of many of his Juſtices in the County; which may be done, and yet it remain a Law, by declaring what is the proper Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine ſenſe, and Conſtruction of words and phraſes in it, and then to ſuffer it to be Executed in no other manner than what's agreable to the ſame. As that though there be never ſo many under <hi>16</hi> years of age, yet it's no Conventicle when there are no more than four of, or above that age, beſides the Houſhold. That no Informers ſhall be Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick witneſſes: that it ſhall be no Conventicle unleſs it can be prov'd, that the Exerciſe of Religion from the beginning to the end thereof, was in other manner than according both to the Liturgie, and practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> That nothing ſhall be judg'd a notorious Evidence, and circumſtance of Fact, but what can be as certain and clear a proof of the Fact, as the Confeſſion of the party, or Oath of two witneſſes, ſo as ſtill to be conſonant that Axiom, <hi>Poſita Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia
<pb facs="tcp:53767:20"/> rei, ponitur res ipſa</hi> (and not to leave it to every Malicious, Indigent, and Avvricious Juſtice, to judg what he pleaſeth to be ſuch an Evidence, and Circumstance) that no Conſtables, Church-wardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be liable to the Mulet of <hi>5 l.</hi> for not executing Warrants for Diſtreſſes, ſeeing the <hi>Act</hi> doth not expreſs it, <hi>page 6.</hi> (the penalty of <hi>5 l.</hi> referring onely to ſuch Officers Neglects of Informing ſome Magiſtrate when he knows, or is credibly Inform'd, Conventicles are held within his Precincts, Pariſh, or Limits, and ſhall not endeavour the conviction of the parties, <hi>pag. 11.</hi> of the <hi>Act</hi> againſt <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi>) that when it is ſaid <hi>pag. 12.</hi> That this <hi>Act,</hi> and all <hi>Clauſes</hi> therein contained, ſhall be conſtrued moſt largely, and beneficially for the Suppreſſing of <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and for the Juſtification and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all perſons to be imployed in the Execution thereof: It muſt be underſtood ſo far as it's agreable to other Laws, Rules of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Reaſon. That no Juſtice of the peace, or chief Magiſtrate, ſhall be ſubject to the Beck of every Informer, to go to any Houſe, or place where he is Inform'd a <hi>Conventicle</hi> is, or elſe forfeit the Sum of <hi>100.</hi> pounds, the Law not Expreſſing it, and that having paid one <hi>100 l.</hi> he can forfeit no more by the Law. And that whoever forfeits one <hi>20 l.</hi> for any Houſe, Out-houſe, Barn, Yard, or Backſide, ſhall be liable to no other forfeiture ever after, by vertue of this <hi>Act,</hi> it not expreſſing it. That Fields not being mentioned in the <hi>Act,</hi> the Owner of them cannot forfeit <hi>20 l. pag. 8.</hi> Notwithſtanding, meeting in ſuch places, make a <hi>Conventicle, pag. 4.</hi> That no Meetings in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Churches for Religious Exerciſes, ſhall be adjudg'd <hi>Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> (a <hi>Conventcile</hi> being properly a Meeting of perſons together clandeſtingly, and in ſome private place for an evil end) for though the Law ſaith, <hi>pag. 4.</hi> That if the Aſſembly be in a <hi>Houſe</hi> where there is a Family Inhabiting, or if it be in a Houſe, Field or place, where there is no Family Inhabiting, then the Magiſtrate upon proof ſhall puniſh them: Yet the word place, though it ſeem to be a Generical term, it cannot Rationally comprehend a publick <hi>Church,</hi> for we muſt ſuppoſe a Law not to be made againſt Reaſon. And it's highly Irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal to judg a <hi>Conventicle</hi> (according to the proper Notion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation of it) which is in ſo publick a place, that every one that pleaſeth may come, and both ſee and hear what is done and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted; the word <hi>place</hi> muſt therefore be ſuch as a Houſe, Field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that it is private in oppoſition to one of publick uſe, by Authoratative appointment. And laſtly, That no Meetings be puniſhed by Law, but
<pb facs="tcp:53767:21"/> at which under pretence of tender conſciences, <hi>Seditious Sectaries,</hi> and other diſloyal perſons contrive Inſurrections (for it's unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any ſhould have the leaſt favoux, that are not of a peaceable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment under his Majeſties Government.) <hi>pag. 3.</hi> And that it may be known whether any ſuch wicked contrivances be at them, let there be particular places for all Parties, and perſwaſions to Meet in, and let his Majeſty appoint whom he ſhall judg moſt fit, to be preſent at their Meetings, to hear and what they Preach, Pray, and Do, and make a true report to him: How far his Majeſty by his Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs (which the <hi>Act</hi> againſt <hi>Conventicles</hi> doth not Invalidate, or Avoid) can Relieve his Subjects diſtreſt other ways, than by the Execution of this <hi>Act,</hi> his own Royal Wiſdom can ſufficient Dictate to him; but if he ſhall judg it fit to do both the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and latter, who can be ſo Diſloyal, or Diſingenuous, as to deny him Heart, Hand, or Purſe, and not clap their Hands, and cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſay, <hi>God Save the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Epoche of that Maxime <hi>(No Biſhop, no King)</hi> is the Reign of that profoundly Wiſe, and Learned King <hi>James,</hi> and no doubt it was then a true political Maxim, becauſe of that general Intereſt they had in this Nation, whereby they could afford conſiderable Support to the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> And it's very requiſite that the Supream Magiſtrate of any Chriſtian Nation, ſhould have a Catholick Intereſt in the <hi>Clergy,</hi> becauſe of the ſwaying and prevailing Influence it hath uſually upon Conſciences, when it's honourable in the Eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but when their Intereſt is ſo debelitated, and languiſheth, being at a low Ebb, and becoming a waning Moon, and ſetting Sun in the Affections, and eſteem of the people, that are moſt conſiderable for Wiſdom and Wealth, and whereof there are many thouſands that did once Revere, and Venerate them) that they are Incapacitated to do that ſervice to Royal Majeſty, that formerly they could. And there is another kind of <hi>Clergy,</hi> whoſe Intereſt is far more conſiderable among the people: Why ſhould it not become a new Maxim in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Politicks <hi>(Maxims of State many times varying with preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and Emergences, unto which they are to be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted few, being calculated for all times, unleſs ſuch as have their foundation in Univerſal truth) No Non-conformiſt, no King.</hi> Let but his Majeſty try further, how far they can be Serviceable to him, and grant them their publick Freedom, and Liberty, to ſerve Lord, and he will find that with all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity, and a Joynt concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conſent, they will ſay, <hi>O King Live for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53767:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
